<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-16"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HappyFrogger Blog</title>
    <link>https://danebalia.com</link>
    <description>A lightweight static site generator</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:33:42 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>HappyFrogger v2.1.0</generator>
    <atom:link href="https://danebalia.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why Bible versions Matter</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/why-i-use-the-kjb.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/why-i-use-the-kjb.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:16:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>faith</category>
      <category>book</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h3 id="why-bible-versions-matter">Why Bible Versions Matter</h3>
<p>To my dearest kids,</p>
<p>I hope one day in the future, when you read this, you will understand why I chose to use the King James Bible (KJB). First I am going to make some bold claims, substantiate them, and then explain why it matters to you. There is much literature on this topic, some very good, some very bad. I will delve into my own personal reasoning and touch on some of the academic side. But ultimately the decision will be yours to make. We have instilled you with what we believe to be the truth, and it is from that foundation we implore you to seek out the truth for yourselves.</p>
<h4 id="the-bible-is-the-word-of-god">The Bible is the Word of God</h4>
<p>The Bible version argument matters, because words are powerful and carry meaning. When you alter the words, you alter the meaning. When you alter the meaning you alter the intent. When you alter the intent, you lose the message of God. So are all Bible versions created equal? No. The King James Bible is the preserved Word of God in the English language and it is inerrant and infallible. Other versions are not.
Other versions take the approach of choosing to either focus on the &quot;meaning&quot; of the text (dynamic equivalence) or a mix of meaning and word-for-word (optimal equivalence). This opens the door to human interpretation and error. The KJB takes a word-for-word approach (formal equivalence) which preserves the original text as closely as possible. This is important because God’s Word is perfect and any deviation from it can lead to misunderstanding and misapplication.</p>
<p>Now are other Bibles heretical? Yes some are clearly flawed and devisive. Other modern versions largely do contain significant sound doctrine and the gospel. If you recall, I was saved and led to the Lord from an NIV. Would I recommend that Bible to you, no, I'll explain shortly. Within these modern translations are subtle changes that can lead to doctrinal errors over time. For example, some versions have altered verses that speak about the deity of Christ, salvation by grace through faith, and the nature of God. These changes can lead to confusion and misinterpretation of essential Christian doctrines. There is much to be said about the men who translated them, but that is for another time. My bigger concern is the base manuscripts they used. The problem is not down to a single set of manuscripts, but a clear division between two families of manuscripts: the Textus Receptus (TR) and the Alexandrian texts. The KJB is based on the Textus Receptus, which has been preserved through the ages and is considered by many scholars to be the most reliable text. Modern versions often rely on the Alexandrian texts, which are older but have been subject to more corruption and alteration over time. This leads to significant differences in key verses that affect doctrine and practice. Not to mention the Alexandrian texts are linked to the Egypt, but also in an area where philosophical and religious ideas contrary to Christianity were born (Gnosticism).</p>
<p>I say all this to say, if we don't have the correct word of God, then we don't have the correct view of God. This is why Bible versions matter.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Disclaimer: For anyone reading this who would like to label me a KJB onlyist or Ruckmanite, I am not. I believe that God can and does use other versions to reach people. I also believe that God can and does use other versions to teach and edify believers. However, I believe that the KJB is the best version available in the English language and it is the one I choose to use and recommend.</p>
</blockquote>
<h4 id="why-i-believe-the-kjb-is-the-preserved-word-of-god">Why I believe the KJB is the preserved Word of God</h4>
<ol>
<li><strong>Divine Preservation</strong>: I believe that God has promised to preserve His Word throughout history (Psalm 12:6-7, Matthew 5:18). The KJB is the culmination of this divine preservation in the English language.</li>
<li><strong>Historical Preservation</strong>: The KJB has a long history of being preserved and used by English-speaking Christians for over 400 years. It has stood the test of time and has been a source of spiritual nourishment for countless believers.</li>
<li><strong>Textual Basis</strong>: The KJB is based on the Textus Receptus, which has been preserved through the ages and is considered by many scholars to be the most reliable text. Modern versions often rely on the Alexandrian texts, which are older but have been subject to more corruption and alteration over time.</li>
<li><strong>Doctrinal Soundness</strong>: The KJB has been shown to be doctrinally sound and consistent with the teachings of the early church. It has been used to defend orthodox Christian beliefs against heresies and false teachings throughout history. I've detailed some of these verses below.</li>
<li><strong>Linguistic Beauty</strong>: The KJB is known for its poetic and majestic language, which has had a profound impact on English literature and culture. Its language has a reverence and dignity that reflects the sacredness of the text.</li>
<li><strong>Education and Language</strong>: The KJB has had a significant impact on the English language and has been a source of education for many generations. Its influence can be seen in literature, art, and culture. Yes it may require a 8th-10th grade education, but too truly unlock the bible takes dedication and study.</li>
<li><strong>Academic Support</strong>: Many scholars and theologians have defended the KJB as the preserved Word of God. Their research and writings provide a strong academic foundation for the belief in the KJB's authenticity and reliability.</li>
<li><strong>Miscommunication in churches</strong>: How does a church with multiple and highly varied Bible versions communicate and labour together effectively? One Bible is in support of female pastors, the other is against it. How can there be many forms of truth from one God? These leads me to the simple deduction, that all Bibles are NOT equal, and there has to be one source of truth. The KJB is that source in the English language.</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="why-i-dont-believe-modern-versions-are-sufficient">Why I don't believe modern versions are sufficient</h4>
<ol>
<li><strong>Doctrinal Errors</strong>: Some modern versions contain subtle changes that can lead to doctrinal errors over time. For example, some versions have altered verses that speak about the deity of Christ, salvation by grace through faith, and the nature of God. For example, some versions change verses that speak about the deity of Christ or the necessity of faith for salvation (John 1:1, Romans 3:28).</li>
<li><strong>Human Interpretation</strong>: Modern versions often take a dynamic equivalence approach, which focuses on the &quot;meaning&quot; of the text rather than a word-for-word translation. This opens the door to human interpretation and error.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Reverence</strong>: Some modern versions use contemporary language that lacks the reverence and dignity of the KJB. This can lead to a casual approach to the text and a lack of appreciation for its sacredness.</li>
<li><strong>Harder to comprehend</strong>: The big argument about modern versions is that it's easier to understand. There is no &quot;thees&quot; and &quot;thous&quot; to get in the way. Honestly, how hard is that to understand? Modern versions actually use more complex and longer words to replace simple ones found in the King James. For example, &quot;commence&quot; instead of &quot;begin&quot;, &quot;utilize&quot; instead of &quot;use&quot;, &quot;endeavor&quot; instead of &quot;try&quot;. I cover this below in more detail.</li>
<li><strong>Aleph and B tied to the Catholic Church</strong>: Vaticanus (B) was catalogued in the Vatican library in 1475, and is still the property of the Vatican. The Catholic Church has a long history of altering and corrupting the Bible, largely because they see the Pope as the ultimate authority on doctrine, not the Bible. That is not our position. We believe the Bible to be the final authority on all matters of faith and practice. Secondly, if you reference the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Trail-Blood-Classic-Account-Persecution/dp/0932762183">Trail of Blood</a> you will see that the Catholic Church was responsible for the persecution and martyrdom of millions of believers throughout history. With these 2 points it leaves me concerned about basing my Bible on manuscripts tied to such an institution.</li>
<li><strong>Omission of Verses</strong>: Some modern versions omit verses that are present in the KJB, which can lead to a loss of important doctrinal teachings. For example, verses like Mark 16:9-20 and John 7:53-8:11 are often omitted in modern versions. Not to mention the Josephine Comma in 1 John 5:7-8 which is completely left out of almost all modern versions.</li>
<li><strong>Use of Questionable Manuscripts</strong>: Modern versions all rely on the Aleph and B (Sinaiticus and Vaticanus).</li>
<li><strong>The Attack on the Deity of Christ</strong>: Here are some of the most significant changes found in the modern versions where Christ's deity is either removed or altered. For simplicity I am just going to compare the KJB to ESV and NASB.</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="completely-omitted-verses-including">17 completely omitted verses including:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Acts 8:37 - &quot;I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God&quot; (entire confession removed)</li>
<li>Matthew 18:11 - &quot;For the Son of man is come to save that which was lost&quot; (mission statement removed)</li>
<li>1 John 5:7 - &quot;the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost: and these three are one&quot; (Trinity statement removed)</li>
<li>Romans 16:24 - &quot;The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all&quot; (benediction removed)</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="additional-verses-with-partial-changes-affecting-christ">29-50 additional verses with partial changes affecting Christ:</h5>
<ul>
<li>1 Timothy 3:16 - &quot;God was manifest&quot; → &quot;He was manifested&quot; (deity statement weakened)</li>
<li>Colossians 1:14 - &quot;through his blood&quot; removed (atonement reference deleted)</li>
<li>John 9:35 - &quot;Son of God&quot; → &quot;Son of Man&quot; (divine title changed to human)</li>
<li>Ephesians 3:9 - &quot;created all things by Jesus Christ&quot; removed
Multiple verses where &quot;Lord Jesus Christ&quot; shortened to just &quot;Christ&quot; or &quot;Jesus&quot;</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="the-most-critical-changes">The Most Critical Changes:</h5>
<ul>
<li>1 Timothy 3:16 - Changes &quot;God was manifest in the flesh&quot; to &quot;He was manifested&quot; - removes explicit statement of God becoming man</li>
<li>1 John 5:7 - Removes &quot;the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost: and these three are one&quot; - explicit Trinity</li>
<li>John 1:18 - Changes &quot;only begotten Son&quot; to &quot;only God&quot; - affects eternal sonship doctrine</li>
<li>Acts 8:37 - Removes &quot;I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God&quot; - impacts salvation confession</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="modern-versions-are-harder-to-read">Modern Versions are harder to read</h4>
<ol>
<li>Precision Requires Technical Terms</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>Example: Romans 12:1</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>KJV: &quot;reasonable service&quot; (simple words)</li>
<li>ESV: &quot;spiritual worship&quot; (longer, harder words)
Why? Better Greek scholarship shows &quot;spiritual&quot; more accurately translates logikēn than &quot;reasonable,&quot; even though it's a harder English word</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2">
<li>False Friends Are Worse Than Hard Words</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>KJV: &quot;Thou shalt not suffer a witch to live&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Computer says</strong>: &quot;5th grade!&quot; (short words)
<strong>Modern reader thinks</strong>: &quot;Don't allow a witch to experience pain&quot;
ACTUAL meaning: &quot;Don't permit a witch to live&quot;
Comprehension: FAIL</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Modern: &quot;You shall not allow a sorceress to live&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Computer says: &quot;8th grade&quot; (longer word)
Modern reader: Immediately understands
Comprehension: SUCCESS</p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Academic Translators Use Academic Vocabulary
ESV/NASB translators are seminary professors and PhDs. They naturally gravitate toward:</li>
</ol>
<p>Theological precision (&quot;predestined,&quot; &quot;propitiation,&quot; &quot;sanctification&quot;)
Academic register (&quot;manifest,&quot; &quot;effectual,&quot; &quot;efficacious&quot;)
Technical accuracy over simplicity</p>
<h4 id="some-common-counter-arguments">Some Common counter arguments</h4>
<ol>
<li><strong>&quot;The KJB is outdated and hard to understand.&quot;</strong> While the language of the KJB may be archaic, it is also rich and poetic. Many believers find that the reverence and dignity of the language enhances their understanding and appreciation of the text. Also, the KJB because of it's poetic style and it's syllabic structure is easier to memorize. Memorization is a key aspect of Bible study and spiritual growth.</li>
<li><strong>Educational Background</strong>: Some argue that modern versions are easier to understand for contemporary readers. While this may be true for some, it is important to remember that the Bible is not just a book to be read casually, but a sacred text that requires reverence and study. If you doing apologetics or deep Bible study, you will need to invest in learning the KJB language anyway. The Bible is it's own dictionary, and learning to navigate it is part of the journey.</li>
<li><strong>&quot;All versions are equally valid.&quot;</strong> While it is true that all versions of the Bible contain elements of truth, not all versions are created equal. The KJB is the preserved Word of God in the English language and is the most reliable and doctrinally sound version available. The NASB, ESV, NIV, and others have significant issues that can lead to doctrinal errors and misunderstandings. The KJB is based on the majority text and all the others are based on the minority text (from Egypt). This is a big deal. What is the symbolism of Egypt in the Bible? It represents falsehood and rebellion against God. Why would we want to base our Bible on manuscripts from such a source?</li>
<li><strong>&quot;Alexandrian manuscripts are older and therefore better.&quot;</strong> While the Alexandrian PAPYRI are genuinely older (P46, P66, P75 from 100-250 AD), the Alexandrian CODICES (Sinaiticus, Vaticanus) CLAIM to be 4th century but have never been scientifically tested. BUT, older does not automatically mean &quot;more origional&quot; or &quot;more accurate&quot;.</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="crucial-books-on-this-topic">Crucial books on this topic</h4>
<ol>
<li>&quot;New Age Bible Versions&quot; by Gail Riplinger</li>
<li>&quot;Why I Believe the King James Bible is the Word of God&quot; by Dr. Peter S. Ruckman</li>
<li>&quot;Greek and Hebrew Study Dangers&quot; by Gail Riplinger</li>
<li>&quot;The King James Bible Defended&quot; by D. A. Waite</li>
</ol>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gods Programme</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/gods-programme.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/gods-programme.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>faith</category>
      <category>book</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h2 id="created-separated-and-good">Created, Separated and Good</h2>
<p>With a bit more understanding about the hidden systems locked inside the Bible and how they can help us understand the Bible better, we reach the next most important mountain peak - God's Programme. God's Programme is about God's plan, not about our own. Rather, about how you should orientate your life, so that it forms part of God's. God's programme and intent is seen visibly in the beginning. Starting in Genesis 1, we see God forming order out of chaos. He does this by creating something or someone perfectly.</p>
<p><a href="verseid:1.1.1">Gen 1:1</a>  In the beginning God created the heaven and the earth.<br />
<a href="verseid:1.1.3">Gen 1:3</a>  And God said, Let there be light: and there was light.<br />
<a href="verseid:1.1.7">Gen 1:7</a>  And God made the firmament<br />
<a href="verseid:1.1.27">Gen 1:27</a>  So God created man in his <em>own</em> image</p>
<p>But he gave these things purpose through the process of separation or the assignment of responsibility - dividing, breaking up or allocating.</p>
<p><a href="verseid:1.1.4">Gen 1:4</a>  And God saw the light, that <em>it was</em> good: and God <strong>divided</strong> the light from the darkness.<br />
<a href="verseid:1.1.6">Gen 1:6</a>  And God said, Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it <strong>divide</strong> the waters from the waters.<br />
<a href="verseid:1.1.9">Gen 1:9</a>  And God said, Let the waters under the heaven be gathered together unto one place, and let the dry <em>land</em> appear: and it was so.<br />
<a href="verseid:1.1.26">Gen 1:26</a>  And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.</p>
<p>We see Adam and Eve, placed in the garden of Eden, separated from the world and unto a purpose. He created Adam and Eve to replenish the earth and subdue it - to have dominion</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The word 'replenish' in the King James Bible is interesting, because it speaks about recovering to former fullness. As if the earth existed prior to the Genesis 1 account of creation. But more about that later.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The last thing to notice, that when God creates something, separates it or gives it responsibility, the next thing He does in that process, is to evaluate it. In Genesis 1, this critical and crucial chapter, we see creation across 6 days, and we see God highlighting 6 times &quot;it was good&quot;. Our God evaluated what was created. Right at the start, at the beginning, God is concerned about whether some is good or not good. In fact, in the last verse of the chapter in the Creation account, God takes a step back, and reflects upon His creation, and says &quot;it was very good&quot;.</p>
<p>It is not enough, that something is made. It is not enough, that something has purpose. But it is enough, that when something is made, separated unto a purpose, that when evaluated, it is found to be good. For something to be good, it does not have to be like God. God did not have to look out at the oceans, the plants and animals, and all He created and ask, &quot;Is this like me?&quot;. Instead, God judged, God discerned and God assessed whether something was good or not, and labelled it such.  Good by definition, is what God thinks, believes and calls good. The definition is tied to God's expectations and assessment.</p>
<h3 id="god-is-not-a-dictator">God is not a dictator</h3>
<p>He created Adam and Eve perfect, but they lacked character. They were babes in the garden. Highly intelligent, but without character. God could create character if He so chose, but what value is there in creating something or someone if you create them as a robot. What kind of God would He be, if He programmed us to only do His will. What kind of God would He be, if He made us nothing more then algorithms geared to only worship and do his bidding. Our lives would be wholly orchestrated, with no choice, or with the appearance of it, but we would be nothing more then the product of those instructions. Imagine having a friend who was a robot. Your friend would be a mirror of your wants and needs. While I am sure this may be pleasurable for a time, ultimately it would become frustrating and empty. This is not a relationship, this is blind obedience and subservience. At it's core, this form of inter-relationship is selfish and is derived of self. A god of this nature is no god at all, and would be more akin to the many tyrants or dictators who at some point tried to gain dominion of the world or a large populace through violence and denial of the will of the individual.</p>
<p>This is not the God of the Bible. If we were programmed for compliance, then our relationship with God would be a mere illusion. Secondly, opportunity to grow, nurture and define our characters would be lost. A country whose people have no character, are no country at all. Character reflects trial, it reflects ethics, it reflects alignment with purpose, it reflects perseverance despite challenges and it deflects self-centredness.</p>
<h2 id="gods-plan">God's Plan</h2>
<p>So then, what is God trying to do with us? He wants to create beings with their own free-will, who will grow to desire Him. <strong>A people that would grow in character to love Him and through that love, experience His fullness (goodness).</strong> Perhaps that could be construed as &quot;selfish&quot;? Well no it is not. If I have something good, I would want to share it with you or with others. Let's consider a basic example. My daughter loves to bake. And when she does, it delights her soul and livens her up. She experiences goodness. And as much she enjoys the process, the outflow from that goodness, she extends to others in our home. She invites them to partake of her baked goods as a natural outflow from goodness itself. To have someone to partake, is to extend that goodness, to advance it to others - to pass it on to others. And as we partake of her baked goods, she experiences delight and so do we. There is a shared experience of goodness.
<strong>Goodness is truly good when it is manifest outside of itself.</strong></p>
<p><a href="verseid:19.34.8">Psa 34:8</a>  O taste and see that the LORD <em>is</em> good: blessed <em>is</em> the man <em>that trusteth in him</em>.</p>
<p>God by all accounts is the fullness of goodness and His desire is for us to partake of that goodness. It is His desire that we would put our trust in Him. That in our trials, in the challenges of this life, we would grow to desire Him with each new day. To have faith in Him. And through that we may experience His goodness on earth, but ultimately one day, experience the full depth of that goodness in heaven, when we behold Him. Heaven is not desirable of itself because its so good. Heaven is desirable, because it is where God lives and where we can experience Him fully. And because of that, it is good, and thus making it a destination we so look forward too. Heaven is our home, but Jesus is the reason we want to dwell there.</p>
<p><a href="verseid:19.27.4">Psa 27:4</a>  One <em>thing</em> have I desired of the LORD, that will I seek after; that I may dwell in the house of the LORD all the days of my life, to behold the beauty of the LORD, and to enquire in his temple.</p>
<h2 id="gods-programme">God's Programme</h2>
<p>To this end, God has created a programme. A schedule or timeline. The Bible outlines this programme clearly for us.</p>
<ol>
<li>God is currently working with His church (those who believe the Gospel) to rapture them and take them Heaven (1 Thess 4:13-18)</li>
<li>God will judge the Church at the Judgement Seat of Christ (2 Cor 5:10), for the degree of goodness of their works.</li>
<li>God will then usher in the tribulation on this earth (Rev 17:14, Rev 6-19). A time of destruction and tremendous challenge for those who did not believe in Christ as Saviour. The AntiChrist will manifest Himself, and be a force to be reckoned with, demanding absolute power and subservience.</li>
<li>God during this period, will return to His promises and work with the nation He called and separated in the Old Testament, the Jews or Israel (Rom 11:25, Rom 11)</li>
<li>At the end of tribulation, Satan will be bound after having deceived many. He will be bound for 1000 years in a bottomless pit (Rev 20:4)</li>
<li>During these 1000 years, there will be peace on earth, as Jesus will reign as authority and King - the Millennial Kingdom (Rev 20:2-7)</li>
<li>At the end of the Millenium, Satan will be judged and punished (Rev 20:10-15).</li>
<li>Thereafter, there will be the Great White Throne of Judgement, for all those who sinned and did not believe in God through faith (Rev 20:14)</li>
<li>Finally, God will create a New Heaven and a New Earth where the righteous will dwell forever (Rev 21:1-3)</li>
</ol>
<p>This is God's timeline, and His programme.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking your Biblical Understanding</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/dispensations.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/dispensations.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>faith</category>
      <category>book</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="unlocking-your-biblical-understanding">[Unlocking your biblical understanding]</h1>
<p>Once I had moved out of my guardians home in KwaZulu Natal, I made my journey into tertiary education or university. I really didn't know what I wanted to do, the life skills I needed to make decisions, wisdom and street smarts were lacking.  My guardians, for the wonderful people that there were in taking me in to stay with, didn't take the time or opportunity to build me up, to encourage, to give me the tools to navigate life. Honestly it was enough that being an orphan, they were willing to feed me, clothe me, share their home with and their kids. And for that I am most thankful.</p>
<p>But being so young, and so ill-equipped I moved through life banging my head, running into endless walls and learning from the hard school of life. I didn't know how to select a career in university. I didn't know how to deal with the social circles. I struggled to understand the meaning and purpose of life. So in university, I did what everyone else. If they drank alcohol and got drunk, well that seemed like a norm, until I ended up at the bottom of a toilet floor of a friends house from over-consumption. Or going to night clubs in the pursuit of finding love, which in hindsight is where you more likely to find more pain then romance. Or being completely ill-equipped with understanding what wholesome, quality relationships were like and being a true friend. I ended up wasting countless hours in tears, in pain, destitute, and while being surrounded with so many friends.</p>
<p>The moral of the story here is a simple one, without the right tools, without being equipped, you going to end up with a tool-belt that consists of a hammer, and everything is going to look like a nail. Hammer's may appear to work well for most things, until you meet the situation, again and again and again. Pain in cycles.</p>
<h2 id="you-need-the-right-tools">You need the right tools</h2>
<p>But here's the clincher. I had the right tools the entire time, I just didn't know how to unlock them. They were in a safe. And the key to their access was the Holy Spirit. And equipping myself with those tools, to use in the right situations, in the right context with the right timing, came from a study and living of God's Word - The Holy Scriptures.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="verseid:55.3.15">2Ti 3:15</a>  And that from a child thou hast known the holy scriptures, which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To equip yourself to navigate this life, you need to develop the tools from the Bible. Why? Because the Bible is the Word of God. If God has inspired His Bible, left us with His very own Words, through the personalities of men. Then these very words, are what we should ponder, consider and meditate on. The Bible is no ordinary book. It is bold in it's claims. Firstly, it does not align itself with other religions. The God of Bible has one identity, is a jealous God and has no tolerance for idolatry or philosophies of men. Secondly, God created the worlds, the universe through His words. His words have power. They form and shape matter, His words direct and define truth, and His words are life. The Bible is not some Neo-orthodox book. It is to be believed literally. It is to be read in a historical, grammatical and literal context. Either the Bible came from God, or it came from men. If it came from men, then I'm not interested in it or it's god. The Bible is not about ideas. The Bible is about words, that form truth. Every word matters.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Proverbs 30:5-6 - &quot;Every word of God is pure: he is a shield unto them that put their trust in him. Add thou not unto his words, lest he reprove thee, and thou be found a liar.&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="but-how-do-we-get-these-tools">But how do we get these tools</h2>
<p>In order to understand the Bible, we need the Holy Spirit. And in order to have that, we need to be saved, by believing on the Lord Jesus Christ, and His work on calvary in paying the ultimate price for our sin. It involves in believing in His resurrection. It involves seeing you sin before a Holy God, and falling down on your knees and calling out to Him.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="verseid:45.10.9">Rom 10:9</a>  That if thou shalt confess with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thine heart that God hath raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The next aspect we need is to be able to understand how to read, study and digest the Bible.  In order to do that, we need to see the natural divisions in the Bible. The first and most clear division is seen in the Old and New Testament. A born-again bible believing Christian, finds their doctrine in the New Testament, not the Old. That is, God's instruction to them is found in the New Testament. Their responsibility and how they will be held accountable is defined there. But also more so, the Old Testament and New Testament are written to two completely different sets of people. The Old Testament is written to Israel and is a record of Israel's history. The New Testament, is largely written to the Church. Following this natural division, is called <strong>Dispensationalism</strong>. For example, as a Christian, we don't have to obey all 600 plus laws in line with the Old Testament for our salvation. We don't have to sacrifice cows, sheep or turtledoves. Those laws, were for Israel. We are not the intended audience.</p>
<h2 id="but-theres-more-divisions">But theres more divisions</h2>
<p>So if there are these two divisions, could there be more? Now that's a great question. And yes there is. Scripture can roughly be broken up into seven main dispensations. A dispensation is biblical word meaning - administration or a division in scripture.  Websters 1828 Dictionary defines it as <em>&quot;The dealing of God to his creatures; the distribution of good and evil, natural or moral, in the divine government&quot;</em>.</p>
<p>We see Adam and Eve in the garden, in their infancy of character, were given an instruction not to eat from the tree of knowledge of good and evil. God told them what the repercussions would be, and it was not spiritual death, it was literal death.</p>
<p>Following that we see men being called to use their consciences, given their knowledge of good and evil. We see Cain and Abel as an example, instructed by God to bring worthy sacrifices, and we see cost and accountability of the actions of men, when they fail to heed God, but follow the evil of their own hearts. Cain kills Abel, and God curses him for the rest of his days.</p>
<p>And so this pattern repeats itself, God imparts instruction, progressive revelation or knowledge. He informs a set of individuals or group what that they are responsible to. And He states how He will hold them accountable to it. To quote Scofield, &quot;A dispensation is a period of time during which man is tested in respect of obediance to some specific revelation of the will of God&quot;.</p>
<p>We will see more clarity to these seven dispensations in the next chapter, but let's understand why dispensations are so important.</p>
<h2 id="why-dispensations-are-so-important">Why dispensations are so important</h2>
<p>It helps us understand what God requires of you in the dispensation you are in. Stated more simplistically,</p>
<ol>
<li>It ensure you don't misapply the Bible to yourself or others. Stated differently, it separates Israel from the Church. They are not the same thing.</li>
<li>It separates the future promises of God, to the Church and Israel.</li>
<li>It separates the three gospels, Gospel of Circumcision, Gospel of Grace and Gospel of the Kingdom.</li>
</ol>
<p>Getting your dispensations right, will help you correctly read, understand and live out the kind of life God desires from you. The Bible is not a book about salvation of men, the Bible is a book that reflects the nature of men, and the glory of God. Through our failures, we see God's faithfulness. Through our sin, we see God's sacrifice. Through our pain, we see God's Power. And through our trials, we see God's care. He is a God of wonder. And the Bible is His book. There are His Words. And not man's. We read the Bible to learn from men, from history but we never lose focus and sight, of the wonder of who the God of the Bible is. Omniscient, omnipotent and omnipresent.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive glory and honour and power: for thou hast created all things, and for thy pleasure they are and were created.&quot;</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="resources-for-understanding-dispensations">Resources for understanding dispensations</h2>
<p>If you interested in understanding the dispensations in your Bible, I would encourage you to look at the following resources.</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Dispensationalism-Charles-C-Ryrie/dp/080242189X?sr=1-1">Charles Ryrie - Dispensationalism</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Greatest-Book-Dispensational-Truth-World/dp/0001473727">Clarence Larkin - Dispensational Truth</a></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/zwDRtBWZqeg?si=PYDnOGXMXlZMbb0t">Video: Are you a dispensationalist?</a></li>
</ol>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Absent man</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/the-absent-man.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/the-absent-man.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>faith</category>
      <category>book</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Watch ye, stand fast in the faith, quit you like men, be strong. - 1 Corinthians 16:13</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Growing up as a young boy in KwaZulu Natal, I remember my mother doing her very best to care for me. My fondest memories of her are her smile upon my face, her cooking what still stands today as some of my favorite foods, but more so her instilling in me a love for God. Life was challenging, perhaps no more so than it is for our kids in this harsh world. I remember my mother, a single parent, and when I looked at her I recall her being lonely. She was always in what felt like the pursuit of a man, a man who could perhaps be a husband for her, and a real dad to me. My father, whom I don't really know, apparently left before I was born. He had met my mother during conscription, resulting in my birth. I don't really know all the details of him, his past, and my knowledge of him is more myth and lore than anything else and probably fits on the tip of a toothpick.</p>
<p>My mother struggled. Perhaps my ability as a child to see her loneliness was reflected in the quality and caliber of poor men who entered our home. Men who tormented my mother either through physical abuse, or men who were nothing but scum of the earth looking for a good time. From ages 1-11, I did not have a father figure in my life. I say 11 years old as that was when my mother died in a car accident; not wearing a seat belt, she broke her neck on impact. I was in the car and ended up with severe injuries. But during those 11 years, there were no men to steer me, to build me up, to equip me with all that it meant to be a MAN.</p>
<p>Our home was a broken home. I hardly felt like my mother spent time with me, but rather was doing her best to provide, to try to fix the missing piece within herself and within our home. That day never came. Given her desire to provide, fix our family, and have her own life, I often felt second place. The depth of loneliness I felt ran deep. I remember on numerous occasions (there were no cell phones), waiting at school as a very young boy, but my mum was not there. Eventually, when the school gates were closed, I would walk home myself, perhaps 2-3 km. I remember walking home one day, crying endlessly. I kept looking back to see if my mother was driving to the school, and while doing so, I fell into a golf dam. Thankfully, a golfer nearby picked me up and took me home. I remember there were times I would be so lonely at home, I would secretly cycle to the entrance of our residential area to try to see if I could find my mother, perhaps at the nearest Spar or making her way home. Loneliness was a friend, a cruel, cruel friend. He punched deep and played many tricks with my mind.</p>
<p>Perhaps it may be said, what kind of woman was this, what kind of mother? For some part of my early life when I left my guardians' home, I thought less of her. But as I now gaze at my three kids, and as I rise onto my own feet in their warm embrace, I see clearly, far more than ever, the realities, the root cause of it all: a failing FATHER and a failed MAN.</p>
<p>There are three phases of my life where FATHER matters. The first was when I was growing up with my mother. The second when I was staying with my guardians. And the third, as I raise my three kids. How different our lives would have been if in my home, a man was present, a husband was there when the wife was not, a father was there when the mother was not. There were so many tools I lacked in my youth that others had. There was so much effort I had to put into building myself into what a real man should be. But of it all, whether in my early life with my mother, or in the latter part of my youth, the description, the qualities, the attributes of what a real man was, were absent.</p>
<p>I look out at the world today, and that picture of what a MAN is feels even further corrupted. We have gender ideologues that have crept in, swaying, self-chosen genders. We have a strong feminist movement that sees women as greater than men, and to some not even needing them. Men and women are certainly equal, before God and before men, but they are different. I want to focus our time in this book on the identity, character, and nature of a real man. By real man, I mean a man who fulfills the role that God has purposed for Him. A man who is strong. A man who fights for what is right. A man who is moral. A man who clings to the word of God. A man who clings to his wife and lays down his life for her. A man who leads his family well. A man who dedicates his time to his kids. But above all, a man who is obedient unto the Lord God, not because God demands, but because God loved him first.</p>
<p>As we journey together, there are three axioms from which this book finds form, but also the clear definition of a REAL MAN, and they are:</p>
<ol>
<li>God (Jesus) is author of this world.</li>
<li>God defines the nature of the roles we should fulfill and how.</li>
<li>Because God is not physically present, we look to His Words in scripture as His stamp of final authority to us. That is, the Bible is the final authority on all matters to do with ethics, truth, relationships, and living.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>All scripture is given by inspiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness: That the man of God may be perfect, thoroughly furnished unto all good works. - 2 Timothy 3:16-17</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I became a REAL MAN because of God's Word. It shaped and moulded me, but above all it allowed me to have a relationship with THE MAN, Christ Jesus.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>🔍 4 Pitfalls in using AI to build software</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/four-pitfalls-ai.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/four-pitfalls-ai.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>tech</category>
      <category>ai</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>AI has evolved into a clear productivity multiplier for developers. Yet some remain skeptical, frustrated by its limitations. The issue often isn't the tool - it's misaligned expectations. Like any powerful technology, success comes from leveraging its strengths rather than fixating on what it can't do.</p>
<p>Through working extensively with AI, I've observed common patterns that hold developers back from realizing its full potential. By understanding these traps, we can better align our expectations and achieve more meaningful outcomes.</p>
<h2 id="pitfall-1-poor-problem-framing">🎯 Pitfall #1: Poor problem framing.</h2>
<p>Problem definition matters. Keywords play such a huge impact it can change the nature of the implementation with or without AI. For example, if I drew a circle, and I stated, <strong>what is this familiar object?</strong> You would immediately state it's a circle. But if I had instead asked, <strong>what is this object?</strong> Perhaps you would find it odd why I would be asking some a basic question, one I already know the answer to. Doubt would creep, perhaps some red flags, resulting in you perhaps asking more questions. Consider a third approach, what if I asked you instead, <strong>what is this unfamiliar object?</strong> This would certainly make you step back and think. How I framed the problem, impacted how you derived your outcome.</p>
<h3 id="how-to-identify">How to identify:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Not thinking through what you are asking, but just asking</li>
<li>Asking for complete solutions without breaking down complex problems</li>
<li>Jumping straight to implementation without discussing architecture</li>
<li>Being vague about edge cases</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pitfall-2-over-reliance-on-ai">🏗️ Pitfall #2: Over-reliance on AI</h2>
<p>Picture a chef asking a kitchen assistant to &quot;just fix dinner service.&quot; Even with access to every ingredient and recipe, the assistant can't replace the chef's experience, judgment, and understanding of their kitchen's unique challenges. Similarly, feeding an AI your entire codebase won't magically solve architectural problems or replace developer intuition.</p>
<h3 id="how-to-identify-1">How to identify:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Expecting AI to understand under-stated requirements</li>
<li>Not reviewing generated code for best practices or logic flaws*</li>
<li>Blindly implementing without understanding</li>
<li>Using AI for critical security or data handling without review</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pitfall-3-providing-insufficient-context">🤖 Pitfall #3: Providing insufficient context</h2>
<p>This is the equivalent of asking a construction company to quote you on building a 3 bedroom house, but forgetting to highlight that the location is on a hill, in a remote location with poor to little infrastructure. You just not going to get the right result.</p>
<h3 id="how-to-identify-2">How to identify:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Not sharing relevant dependencies or environment details</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Omitting important business rules or constraints</li>
<li>Not explaining how the code fits into the larger system</li>
<li>Failing to specify performance requirements or scale</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pitfall-4-ineffective-iteration">🔄 Pitfall #4: Ineffective iteration</h2>
<p>Fred is building his dream bathroom with a view of the mountains. Initially, he tells the builder &quot;Move the toilet to the left and bath to the right&quot; to capture that perfect vista. The builder does exactly that, rearranging the plumbing at considerable effort. The next day, Fred has another thought: &quot;Actually, what if we just kept everything where it was and moved the window instead?&quot; The builder, trying to accommodate, moves the window. But Fred had forgotten a crucial detail from his first design - the original window position had needed special tinted glass to manage the intense morning sun. When Fred visits the site, he finds a beautiful mountain view...and a bathroom that turns into a greenhouse every sunrise.</p>
<h3 id="how-to-identify-3">How to identify:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Not providing feedback on what worked/didn't work</li>
<li>Starting over instead of building on previous responses</li>
<li>Not clarifying misunderstandings in the AI's assumptions</li>
<li>Failing to narrow down issues when debugging</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="suggestions">Suggestions:</h2>
<h3 id="improve-your-prompt-engineering">Improve your prompt engineering</h3>
<p>One aspect of this is prompt engineering, and the second around structured communication. There is a plenitude of improvement and thinking around this on the internet, and a great resource in the <a href="https://www.promptingguide.ai/">Prompt Engineering Guide</a>.</p>
<h3 id="see-ai-as-a-collaborative-junior-developer">See AI as a collaborative junior developer</h3>
<p>The real power comes from treating AI as a collaborative junior developer - one who can suggest approaches, spot patterns, and help with implementation details, but needs your guidance and domain expertise to create truly effective solutions. Like any good mentoring relationship, success comes from clear communication, thoughtful questions, and combining both parties' strengths.</p>
<h3 id="improve-problem-definition">Improve Problem Definition</h3>
<p>Here's a simple template for an improved problem definition:</p>
<pre><code>Here's what I'm trying to achieve: [clear goal]
Current environment: [versions, dependencies]
Constraints: [performance, security, etc.]
What I've tried: [previous attempts]
Specific questions: [what you need help with]
</code></pre>
<p>For more complex problems:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">// Context
System: [architecture, tech stack, scale]
Dependencies: [versions, integrations]
Constraints: [performance, security, compliance]

// Current State
Existing code: [relevant snippets]
Current behavior: [what's happening]
Error messages: [if applicable]

// Desired Outcome
Expected behavior
Success criteria
Non-functional requirements

// Attempted Solutions
Approaches tried
Results observed
Specific blockers

// Specific Questions
Targeted questions about implementation
Areas needing clarification
Potential concerns
</code></pre>
<p>Include diagrams or flow-charts as well.</p>
<h3 id="improving-iterative-development">Improving Iterative Development</h3>
<pre><code>Initial code: [code snippet]
Issues found: [specific problems]
Required changes: [clear modifications needed]
New requirements: [additional features]
</code></pre>
<h3 id="improving-development-experience">Improving development experience</h3>
<p>Keep AI and context awareness separate from your IDE. While mastering these fundamentals, limit in-IDE AI to Copilot for routine code completion. Use standalone AI tools like Claude (Project Mode) or ChatGPT externally. This separation offers three key advantages:</p>
<ol>
<li>Control over AI model quality</li>
<li>Better context management</li>
<li>Easier recovery from context-related mistakes</li>
</ol>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survey of the Bible</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/bible.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/bible.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>faith</category>
      <category>book</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="understanding-the-bibles-timeline-and-books">Understanding the Bible's Timeline and Books</h1>
<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>
<p>The Bible contains 66 books written over about 1,500 years. While these books appear in a certain order in our Bibles, they weren't written in that same order. Understanding when they were written helps us better understand their message and context.</p>
<h2 id="new-testament-timeline">New Testament Timeline</h2>
<p>The New Testament books were written between 45-96 AD. Surprisingly, James was actually the first book written (around 45 AD), not Matthew! The last book written was Revelation (around 95-96 AD).</p>
<h2 id="old-testament-timeline">Old Testament Timeline</h2>
<p>While Genesis is the first book in our Bibles, Job was likely written first during the time of Abraham. After Job, Moses wrote Genesis and the other four books of the Law (Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy).</p>
<h1 id="focus-on-jude">Focus on Jude</h1>
<h2 id="quick-facts">Quick Facts</h2>
<ul>
<li>Written: Around 67-68 AD</li>
<li>Author: Jude, one of Jesus' brothers</li>
<li>Audience: Christians facing false teachers</li>
<li>Length: Just 25 verses - one chapter!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="who-was-jude">Who Was Jude?</h2>
<p>Jude was Jesus' half-brother (they shared the same mother, Mary). Interestingly, he doesn't introduce himself as &quot;Jesus' brother&quot; but as &quot;a servant of Jesus Christ.&quot; This shows his humility and recognition that Jesus was more than just his family member - He was his Lord and Savior!</p>
<h2 id="main-message">Main Message</h2>
<p>Jude's main message is simple but powerful: &quot;Stand firm for true Christian teaching.&quot; He warns believers about false teachers who had secretly entered the church and were twisting God's grace into an excuse for immoral behavior.</p>
<h2 id="key-points-to-remember">Key Points to Remember</h2>
<ol>
<li>Christians need to actively &quot;contend&quot; (struggle, fight) for true faith</li>
<li>False teachers had infiltrated the church, misusing God's grace</li>
<li>Jude uses Old Testament examples to warn about God's judgment on rebellion</li>
<li>He gives practical advice for staying strong in faith</li>
<li>Contains unique information about spiritual warfare (like Michael the archangel's dispute over Moses' body)</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="why-it-matters-today">Why It Matters Today</h2>
<p>While written nearly 2,000 years ago, Jude's message is still relevant. Christians today still need to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Know what they believe and why</li>
<li>Be able to recognize false teaching</li>
<li>Stand firm for truth while showing love</li>
<li>Remember God's faithfulness in the past</li>
</ul>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Table of Contents</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/mans-guide-chapter-0.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/mans-guide-chapter-0.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>faith</category>
      <category>book</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="contents">Contents</h1>
<h2 id="section-i-understanding-the-foundation">📚 Section I: Understanding the Foundation</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Getting oriented with God's Word</p>
</blockquote>
<ol>
<li><a href="./the-absent-man.html">Chapter 1: The Absent man</a></li>
<li><a href="./dispensations.html">Chapter 2: Unlocking your Bible Understanding</a></li>
<li><a href="./gods-programme.html">Chapter 3: God's Eternal Programme</a></li>
<li><a href="./why-i-use-the-kjb.html">Chapter 4: Why Bible versions Matter</a></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="section-ii-the-journey-of-salvation">⚡ Section II: The Journey of Salvation</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>The core of Christian faith and life</p>
</blockquote>
<ol start="4">
<li>The Gospel Message</li>
<li>The Blessings in Salvation</li>
<li>The Cross of Salvation</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="section-iii-the-challenges-after-salvation">🛡️ Section III: The Challenges after Salvation</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>The struggles of this life</p>
</blockquote>
<ol start="7">
<li>Overcoming Sin</li>
<li>Losing Salvation</li>
<li>Rejecting Calvinism</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="section-iv-the-courage-of-sanctification">🤺 Section IV: The Courage of Sanctification</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>The opportunities within this life</p>
</blockquote>
<ol start="10">
<li>Preparing to Evangelize</li>
<li>Preparing to Preach</li>
<li>Preparing to Teach</li>
<li>Preparing for Marriage</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="section-v-biblical-manhood-through-examples">👥 Section V: Biblical Manhood through Examples</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Lessons from the lives of others</p>
</blockquote>
<ol start="10">
<li>Satan in the Bible</li>
<li>Joshua in the Bible</li>
<li>Jonah in the Bible</li>
<li>Joseph in the Bible</li>
<li>Jesus in the Bible</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="section-v-deeper-study-resources">🔍 Section V: Deeper study resources</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Additional tools for life</p>
</blockquote>
<ol start="15">
<li><a href="./bible.html">Notes on each Book of the Bible</a></li>
<li>Why I use the King James Bible</li>
</ol>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The King is Coming</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/the-king-is-coming.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/the-king-is-coming.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 08:16:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>creative</category>
      <category>poem</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-king-is-coming">The King is Coming</h1>
<p>Up in the sky, the tempests rage,<br />
as the heaven's proclaim the coming age,<br />
where Jesus the Lamb, breaks vials of his own,<br />
as he pours out their tears all over his throne.<br />
His fury and wrath ascends to the highest,<br />
and shall descend to the deepest, where the darkest liest.</p>
<p>Down on the earth, in the land of men,<br />
The people dance and sing in their wicked den,<br />
Praising self, rejecting Him, denouncing the Cross<br />
Living their best life at great cost.<br />
They live to enjoy each new day,<br />
And steep themselves in comforts of rich array.</p>
<p>High up in heaven, the Lord mounts His horse,<br />
and prepares to descend and evil divorce,<br />
His Word like a sword proceeds from His mouth,<br />
As He commands his armies to gather out.<br />
Down to the earth they go,<br />
The righteous will avail with mighty bow.</p>
<p>In Sodom and Gomorrah, they see the signs,<br />
The earth is groaning but they remain benign.<br />
Flashes scatter across they sky,<br />
As the Lord breaks open every wretched lie.<br />
The fire and fury of His descendance unknown,<br />
As He comes to grant vengence to His very own.</p>
<p>Be-warned, be wary, murmur not and complain,<br />
For Jesus is coming, coming again,<br />
To rule and to reign,<br />
To scatter the rain,<br />
To dry up our tears,<br />
And wrestle all fears,<br />
Jesus, Jesus the King,<br />
Is coming again.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2025 Reading List</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/2025-reading.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/2025-reading.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 08:16:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>creative</category>
      <category>reading</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/classic_library.png" alt="2025 Reading List" /></p>
<h2 id="didnt-complete">Didn't complete</h2>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Never-Split-Difference-Negotiating-Depended-ebook/dp/B014DUR7L2">Never Split the Difference - Chris Voss</a></li>
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/boilerplate/Refactoring.html">Refactoring - Martin Fowler</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/No-Asshole-Rule-Building-Civilized/dp/0446526568">The No Asshole Rule - Robert Sutton</a></li>
<li><a href="https://leanpub.com/cloudstrategy">Cloud Strategy - Gregor Hohpe</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/AI-Engineering-Chip-Huyen/dp/1098103243">AI Engineering - Chip Huyen</a></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="read">Read</h2>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3.Harry_Potter_and_the_Sorcerer_s_Stone">The Philosopher's Stone - JK Rowling</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/106692.The_Sword_in_the_Stone">The Sword in the Stone - T.H. White</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Angular-Design-Patterns-Best-Practices/dp/1786461725">Angular Design Patterns and Best Practices - Alvaro Camillo Neto</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/New-Age-Bible-Version-Riplinger/dp/0932762213">New Age Bible Version - Gail Riplinger</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Faith-More-Than-You-Think/dp/1616441380">Faith: More than you think - Mike Pearl</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/68428.Mistborn">Mistborn - Brandon Sanderson</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/68429.The_Well_of_Ascension">The Well of Ascension - Brandon Sanderson</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Exploring-Minor-Prophets-John-Phillips/dp/0802412015">Exploring the Minor Prophets - John Phillips</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/AI-Driven-Leader-Harnessing-Smarter-Decisions/dp/B0DB8QL3ZK">The AI-Driven Leader - Geoff Wood</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/68430.Elantris">Elantris - Brandon Sanderson</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/New-Age-Bible-Version-Riplinger/dp/0932762213">New Age Bible Versions - Gail Riplinger</a></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="planned">Planned</h2>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://craftinginterpreters.com/">Robert Nystrom - Crafting Intepreters</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15842786-understanding-computation">Tom Stuart - Understanding Computation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://geraldmweinberg.com/Site/QSM_vol_1.html">Gerald Weinberg - Quality Software Management, Vol 1: Systems Thinking</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Thinking-Systems-Donella-H-Meadows/dp/1603580557">Donella Meadows - Thinking in Systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1491983647?tag=bbookshub-20&amp;linkCode=ogi&amp;th=1&amp;psc=1">Brendan Burns - Designing Distributed Systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.larkinestate.com/books/dispensational-truth.html">Clarence Larking - Dispensational Truth</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Betsy Beyer - Site Reliability Engineering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bookshop.org/books/rationality-what-it-is-why-it-seems-scarce-why-it-matters/9780525561996">Steven Pinker - Rationality: What It Is, Why It Seems Scarce, Why It Matter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Lies-My-Govt-Told-Me-ebook/dp/B09R4Y6YKJ/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=lies+my+government+told+me+robert+malone&amp;qid=1673239997&amp;s=digital-text&amp;sprefix=lies%2Cdigital-text%2C455&amp;sr=1-1">Lies My Gov't Told Me: And the Better Future Coming</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B09PZ9X17W/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_d_asin_title_o00?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">Traced: Human DNA's Big Surprise</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Accelerate-Software-Performing-Technology-Organizations-ebook/dp/B07B9F83WM">Jez-Humble, Gene Kim - Accelerate: The Science of Lean Software and DevOps: Building and Scaling High Performing Technology Organizations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.brendangregg.com/blog/2020-07-15/systems-performance-2nd-edition.html">Brendan Gregg - Systems Performance</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Site Reliability Engineering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Building secure &amp; reliable systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/building-evolutionary-architectures/9781492097532/">Neal Ford, Rebecca Parsons - Building Evolutionary Architectures</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hard-Thing-About-Things-Building/dp/0062273205">The Hard Thing About Hard Things - Ben Horowitz</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-General-Systems-Thinking-ebook/dp/B004VS9AUS/?_encoding=UTF8&amp;pd_rd_w=ceglc&amp;content-id=amzn1.sym.cf86ec3a-68a6-43e9-8115-04171136930a&amp;pf_rd_p=cf86ec3a-68a6-43e9-8115-04171136930a&amp;pf_rd_r=138-2750200-6069238&amp;pd_rd_wg=RcZwU&amp;pd_rd_r=680c1234-d2b8-45bc-a398-8acb35ad454c&amp;ref_=aufs_ap_sc_dsk">Introduction to General Systems Thinking - Gerald Weinberg</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Return-God-Hypothesis-Compelling-Scientific/dp/0062071505">Return of the God Hypothesis - Dr. Stephen Meyer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Building-LLMS-Scratch-Practical-Approach-ebook/dp/B09QZQZQZQ">Building LLMS from scratch </a></li>
</ol>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2026 Reading List</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/2026-reading.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/2026-reading.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 08:16:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>creative</category>
      <category>reading</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/classic_library.png" alt="2026 Reading List" /></p>
<h2 id="currently-reading">Currently Reading</h2>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Never-Split-Difference-Negotiating-Depended-ebook/dp/B014DUR7L2">Never Split the Difference - Chris Voss</a></li>
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/boilerplate/Refactoring.html">Refactoring - Martin Fowler</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/No-Asshole-Rule-Building-Civilized/dp/0446526568">The No Asshole Rule - Robert Sutton</a></li>
<li><a href="https://leanpub.com/cloudstrategy">Cloud Strategy - Gregor Hohpe</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/AI-Engineering-Chip-Huyen/dp/1098103243">AI Engineering - Chip Huyen</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Platform-Strategy-Leveraging-Ecosystems-Business/dp/1492076893">Platform Strategy - Gregor Hohpe</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Fundamentals-Data-Engineering-Joe-Reis/dp/1492062575">Fundamentals of Data Engineering - Joe Reis &amp; Matt Housley</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Designing-Machine-Learning-Systems-Chip/dp/109810827X">Designing Machine Learning Systems - Chip Huyen</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Exploring-Gospel-John-Phillips-Commentary/dp/0825434890"> Exploring Gospel of John - John Phillips</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hero-Ages-Book-Three-Mistborn/dp/1250868319"> Hero of Ages - Brandon Sanderson</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Build-Large-Language-Model-Scratch/dp/1633437167">Building an LLM from Scratch - Sebastian Raschka</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Intentional-Father-Practical-Courage-Character/dp/0801018684"> The Intentional Father - Jon Tyson</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.larkinestate.com/books/dispensational-truth.html"> Dispensational Truth - Clarence Larkin</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Why-Machines-Learn-Elegant-Behind/dp/0593185749"> Why Machines Learn - Anil Anantaswamy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Kettlebell-Simple-Sinister-Revised-Updated/dp/0989892433"> Kettlebell: Simple and Sinister - Pavel Tsatsouline</a></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="planned">Planned</h2>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://craftinginterpreters.com/">Robert Nystrom - Crafting Intepreters</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15842786-understanding-computation">Tom Stuart - Understanding Computation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://geraldmweinberg.com/Site/QSM_vol_1.html">Gerald Weinberg - Quality Software Management, Vol 1: Systems Thinking</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Thinking-Systems-Donella-H-Meadows/dp/1603580557">Donella Meadows - Thinking in Systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1491983647?tag=bbookshub-20&amp;linkCode=ogi&amp;th=1&amp;psc=1">Brendan Burns - Designing Distributed Systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.larkinestate.com/books/dispensational-truth.html">Clarence Larking - Dispensational Truth</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Betsy Beyer - Site Reliability Engineering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bookshop.org/books/rationality-what-it-is-why-it-seems-scarce-why-it-matters/9780525561996">Steven Pinker - Rationality: What It Is, Why It Seems Scarce, Why It Matter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Lies-My-Govt-Told-Me-ebook/dp/B09R4Y6YKJ/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=lies+my+government+told+me+robert+malone&amp;qid=1673239997&amp;s=digital-text&amp;sprefix=lies%2Cdigital-text%2C455&amp;sr=1-1">Lies My Gov't Told Me: And the Better Future Coming</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B09PZ9X17W/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_d_asin_title_o00?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">Traced: Human DNA's Big Surprise</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Accelerate-Software-Performing-Technology-Organizations-ebook/dp/B07B9F83WM">Jez-Humble, Gene Kim - Accelerate: The Science of Lean Software and DevOps: Building and Scaling High Performing Technology Organizations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.brendangregg.com/blog/2020-07-15/systems-performance-2nd-edition.html">Brendan Gregg - Systems Performance</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Site Reliability Engineering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Building secure &amp; reliable systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/building-evolutionary-architectures/9781492097532/">Neal Ford, Rebecca Parsons - Building Evolutionary Architectures</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hard-Thing-About-Things-Building/dp/0062273205">The Hard Thing About Hard Things - Ben Horowitz</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-General-Systems-Thinking-ebook/dp/B004VS9AUS/?_encoding=UTF8&amp;pd_rd_w=ceglc&amp;content-id=amzn1.sym.cf86ec3a-68a6-43e9-8115-04171136930a&amp;pf_rd_p=cf86ec3a-68a6-43e9-8115-04171136930a&amp;pf_rd_r=138-2750200-6069238&amp;pd_rd_wg=RcZwU&amp;pd_rd_r=680c1234-d2b8-45bc-a398-8acb35ad454c&amp;ref_=aufs_ap_sc_dsk">Introduction to General Systems Thinking - Gerald Weinberg</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Return-God-Hypothesis-Compelling-Scientific/dp/0062071505">Return of the God Hypothesis - Dr. Stephen Meyer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Building-LLMS-Scratch-Practical-Approach-ebook/dp/B09QZQZQZQ">Building LLMS from scratch </a></li>
</ol>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guideposts to Measuring Developers</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/measuring-developers.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/measuring-developers.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>tech</category>
      <category>leadership</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/MeasuringDevelopers.png" alt="MeasuringDevs" /></p>
<p>Measuring developer productivity is a hot and controversial topic, and there have been many contributions from the likes
of McKinsey, Kent Beck, Dan North, Gergely Orosz that deal with the subject matter from both sides (we can measure
accurately vs. measuring is hard). My intent is to rather provide guideposts to the leader placed in a position to
measure developer productivity. What should he or she do if the request is part of compliance with business executives?
Or how can they get comfortable with the idea, and how can they take the next steps?</p>
<h2 id="the-driving-forces">The Driving Forces</h2>
<p>Now the need to measure can come from two forces: an external request from business or an internal demand to improve. In
the former case, where an executive team or manager is requesting metrics, we will call this compliance. In the second
case, where a leader and member of the delivery team want to improve, we will call this autonomy. Autonomy because there
are fewer constraints and a greater ability to succeed in measuring relative to the context of the team and its
practices.</p>
<h3 id="guidepost-1-why">Guidepost 1: Why?</h3>
<p>But before we begin any journey, we must ask: Why? This seems like an obvious question, but in some organizations, it is
a very difficult question to get the answer to. Some organizations may require it with the solid intent of improving
continuous delivery. Or executives might pursue it to create some sense of tangible measure of performance (like that
seen in sales/manufacturing). Another might be an engineering manager frustrated with an inability to generate impact
from a highly skilled team of developers. Both require different strategies, but ultimately, it's important to
understand why they're being done.</p>
<ol>
<li>What is the perceived outcome of measuring developer productivity?</li>
<li>Why is this outcome necessary?</li>
<li>Could the outcome be a side-effect or is it a root-cause?</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="compliance">Compliance:</h2>
<h3 id="guidepost-2-behavioral-change">Guidepost 2: Behavioral Change</h3>
<p>In terms of compliance, acceptance initially is key to granting you the room and space to be effective in communicating,
inquiring, and sharing potential concerns. A fundamental question to ask is: if we did measure or leverage a set of
measures and their results were negative; would they result in a change of behavior? More specifically, would business,
management, or leadership invest to create the change they want. Is the lemon worth the squeeze?</p>
<h3 id="guidepost-3-define">Guidepost 3: Define</h3>
<p>In compliance, it's very important to clarify terminology. One such word is <strong>productivity</strong>. We want more productive
developers, sure, but what does that mean? Stable systems less features; unstable systems, rapid features. Iron out the
terminology and be sure both parties are talking about the same thing.</p>
<h3 id="guidepost-4-devise">Guidepost 4: Devise</h3>
<p>In compliance, and if available, distill your concerns into well-articulated thoughts. When I was presented with the
requirement to measure my teams, my first thought was DON'T. Inherently, all my years of experience as a developer and
in leading teams had created a mental and abstract gate on my pre-frontal cortex that raised a red flag, but I was
unable to articulate it effectively to others. Particularly business executives.</p>
<p>Recently, I sat down and did so, and these are my concerns/challenges to measuring developers:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Misuse</strong>: loss of understanding of individual teams and how they operate, thus enforcing behavior that does not
align with or correlate to the team's practices.</li>
<li><strong>Misinterpretation</strong>: Strategic decisions taken with generalized data across many teams that lead to large shifts in
investments (time and money)</li>
<li><strong>Misalignment</strong>: Metrics in isolation are not silver bullets. Meetings may be considered the No. 1 hindrance to deep
work. But in viciously addressing it, we could see strong declines in company culture and collaboration.</li>
<li><strong>Misplaced</strong>: A set of metrics is applied to achieve an outcome, but despite the positive nature of those metrics,
it has little to no effect on that outcome.</li>
<li><strong>Misdirection</strong>: The metrics give the business a false sense that all teams are delivering well and equally because
of their numeric compliance (Goodhart's Law).</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="guidepost-5-derive">Guidepost 5: Derive</h3>
<p>If you do have the ability to aid in the metrics that can be leveraged to measure developers' performance, don't depend
on any single metric. There are no silver bullets. Secondly, try making it a three-tier set of measures.</p>
<ol>
<li>With a people-based focus, this is about perceptions of how people feel or experience things.</li>
<li>With a system-based focus, this is about attaining more factual or hard truths about the performance of systems.3.
With a user-centric focus, this is about deciphering and honing in on the right outcomes of the consumed output.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="guidepost-6-partnership">Guidepost 6: Partnership</h3>
<p>This is a crucial part, don't become the enemy of business or management. Rather, partner and see the journey as an
experiment. Partnerships are a great mechanism for achieving the right outcomes, as they enable you to communicate
concerns with a-lot more ease.</p>
<h2 id="autonomy">Autonomy</h2>
<p>With autonomy, the journey should be the same: why and to what outcome, and how will measuring productivity attain it.
It could often be an experiment to understand different measures and assess their worth and impact. But the worst thing
you could do is to have metrics or measures for the sake of having them.</p>
<h3 id="guidepost-7-mental-frameworks">Guidepost 7: Mental Frameworks</h3>
<p>If you are clear on your outcome, there are three strongly supported mental frameworks for measuring developer
productivity. I won't go into the details of each here, but they are worth reading up on. That is the problem each is
trying to address and the value you could derive from leaning on them.</p>
<h3 id="d.o.r.a">D.O.R.A</h3>
<h4 id="use-case">Use case</h4>
<p>If you are interested in migrating teams towards small changes, frequently deployed. This is great for teams that are
still largely waterfall. DORA is meant to track delivery practices and measure them, not the productivity of people.</p>
<h3 id="s.p.a.c.e">S.P.A.C.E</h3>
<h4 id="use-case-1">Use case</h4>
<p>The focus of SPACE is to clarify developer productivity, but to also focus on more than just systems, but how people
consume those systems. It's more of a holistic view of the software development lifecycle by not only improving how
software is produced, but also optimizing how it is consumed within the organization.</p>
<h3 id="devex">DEVEX</h3>
<h4 id="use-case-2">Use case</h4>
<p>DevEx is concerned with the overall experience of developers. The problems it addresses are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Tooling and infrastructure</li>
<li>Processes and Practices</li>
<li>Culture and feedback</li>
</ol>
<p>DevEx focuses on making the development process more enjoyable and productive, which can lead to faster development
cycles, higher quality software, and more innovation.</p>
<p>A helpful analogy for understanding the aims of these 3 studies is the following:</p>
<p><img src="images/pizza.png" alt="alt text" /></p>
<p>Hope that helps :)</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reverse Engineering Chaos Through Blackholes</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/blackholes.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/blackholes.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>tech</category>
      <category>leadership</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h3 id="what-do-i-mean-by-chaos">1. What do I mean by &quot;chaos&quot;?</h3>
<p>Chaos surrounds us; it’s ubiquitous. Just consider the second law of thermodynamics, which asserts that everything tends toward disorder. Whether in our personal lives through imbalances, tragedies, or simply the daily pressures of work, chaos is a thread that connects us all. We may not experience chaos at the same time, in the same way, or in the same place, but inevitably, it will appear, as surely as sparks fly upward.</p>
<p>Reflecting on my own life and the challenges I’ve faced over a lengthy career in various roles—Linux Administrator, Development Manager, Developer, and now Team Lead—I sought to apply a new dimension of thought to these challenges. What am I not seeing? What can I learn better? So, I turned my gaze to outer space and the most powerful chaotic entity in our known universe: black holes. If this entity epitomizes all things disorganized, disruptive, and destructive, what can I learn from its design and nature? More importantly, how can I apply those lessons to the chaos that surrounds us? This introspection led me to black holes.</p>
<h3 id="terminology">2. Terminology</h3>
<p>Let's build up to what a blackhole is by going through some grounding in terms of terminology that we will use later.</p>
<p><img src="images/gravity.jpg" alt="Gravity" /></p>
<p><strong>Gravity</strong>: The force that attracts objects with mass towards one another. In black holes, gravity is incredibly strong, distorting space-time.</p>
<p><strong>Space-time</strong>: Space-time is the four-dimensional fabric that combines space and time, shaping how objects move and interact under the influence of gravity. Or said differently, space-time is often referred to as the fabric of space because it combines the three dimensions of space and the one dimension of time into a single, interconnected framework that can be warped by mass and energy.</p>
<p><img src="images/blackhole.jpg" alt="Blackhole" /></p>
<p><strong>Blackhole</strong>: A region of space where the gravitational field is so strong that nothing, not even light, can escape from it.</p>
<p><strong>Singularity:</strong> The singularity of a black hole is a point at its very center where gravity is so strong that it crushes all matter into an infinitely small space with infinite density.</p>
<p><strong>Accretion Disk</strong>: is a swirling ring of gas, dust, and other material that forms around a black hole</p>
<p><strong>Event Horizon</strong>: The boundary surrounding a black hole beyond which no light or other information can escape.</p>
<p><strong>Tidal Forces:</strong> Tidal forces are the differences in gravitational pull on different parts of an object, stretching it when near a massive body like a black hole.</p>
<p><strong>Spaghettification</strong>: The process by which an object would be stretched and elongated as it falls into a black hole due to extreme tidal forces. Your head and your feet would experience different forces as your feet would get pulled into long strands spaghetti-like that would stretch you towards the singularity.</p>
<p><strong>Hawking Radiation</strong>: The theoretical radiation predicted by Stephen Hawking that black holes can emit due to quantum effects, potentially causing them to lose mass and evaporate over time.</p>
<ol>
<li><p><strong>Quantum Effects</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Near the event horizon of a black hole, quantum mechanics predicts that particle-antiparticle pairs can spontaneously form.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Particle Pairs</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Normally, these pairs annihilate each other quickly. However, at the event horizon, one particle can fall into the black hole while the other escapes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Energy Loss</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>The escaping particle takes energy away from the black hole. This energy loss appears as radiation emitted by the black hole.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Black Hole Evaporation</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Over a very long time, this process causes the black hole to lose mass and energy, potentially leading to its eventual evaporation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="images/relativity.jpg" alt="Relativity" /></p>
<p><strong>Special relativity:</strong> (1905) Einstein’s theory dealing with the physics of objects moving at constant speeds, especially near the speed of light, and how time and space are relative.</p>
<p><strong>General relativity:</strong> (1915) Einstein’s theory describing how gravity affects the fabric of space-time, predicting phenomena like black holes (mass and energy)</p>
<p><img src="images/minkowski.jpg" alt="Minkowski" /></p>
<p><strong>Minkowski diagram:</strong> is a space-time diagram used in special relativity to visualize events. It typically includes two axes: time (vertical) and space (horizontal).Light cones represent the paths light would take, forming a 45-degree angle with the axes.</p>
<p><strong>Penrose diagram:</strong> also known as a conformal diagram. Is a way of representing spacetime that simplifies the structure of infinity to a finite distance, allowing the entire infinite spacetime to be depicted in a finite diagram. This very similar to a picture of the earth, Mercator diagram, where the sizes of the continents are obscured or compromised so the angles can be protected. The intent is to allow for navigation and moving around the earth as a ship for example. In the Penrose, it is the same concept but to the effect where infinity is compromised (reduced) so we can reason about infinite spacetime.</p>
<h3 id="quiz-of-misconceptions">3. Quiz of Misconceptions?</h3>
<p><img src="images/fall.jpg" alt="Fall" /></p>
<p>3.1 What would happen if you fell into a blackhole?</p>
<ul>
<li>If you fell into a black hole, you’d experience extreme tidal forces stretching you out (<strong>spaghettification</strong>) as you approach the <strong>event horizon,</strong> the point of no return. Time would slow down for you compared to outside observers, making you appear to freeze at the horizon. Once inside, you’d continue falling towards the <strong>singularity</strong>, where gravity becomes infinitely strong, and space-time curvature is infinite, like an ultimate crash point where all known physics breaks down. This journey into the black hole would be a one-way trip with no escape.</li>
<li>Another theory is that you would hit some kind of fire wall, and just explode.</li>
<li>Either way, you die.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="images/firewall.jpg" alt="Explode" /></p>
<p>3.2 A blackhole is a vacuum</p>
<ul>
<li>A blackhole is not a vacuum. A vacuum by definition is empty space. A blackhole on the other hand as witnessed by accretion disk contains matter and gases, facing extreme pressure of gravity.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="chaos-in-software-development">4. Chaos in Software Development</h2>
<h3 id="lesson-chaos-has-a-hidden-order">4.1  Lesson: Chaos has a Hidden Order</h3>
<p><img src="images/poller.jpg" alt="Poller" /></p>
<h4 id="the-elegant-solution-gone-bad">4.1.1 The Elegant Solution Gone Bad</h4>
<p>If there is one clear guarantee, it is that in whatever role you are in, you will face a situation that presents a problem impacting someone, yet on the surface makes no sense or is complex and potentially challenges reason. Developers commonly encounter this when troubleshooting software defects. I faced one such situation with our high-throughput, highly multi-threaded monitoring architecture. We were polling over 12,000 devices and extracting about 60 billion data points a month, using nearly 40 MySQL servers to gather real-time metrics about machine health so we could notify customers when their machines were in jeopardy.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, we hit an issue where we were losing data for new devices with long names because we used the device name, customer name, and date as table names for storing data. MySQL has a table name limit of 64 characters. I implemented a fix, which was just three lines of code to generate a hash of the name. It felt like an ideal, simple, and highly effective solution. I was so proud. All testing indicated it worked and integrated beautifully across our systems. It went live, and the process was smooth. I had followed the system through two proven examples, and I now had confirmation it had worked. YAY!</p>
<p>A week later, the key nodes responsible for flushing data to the database from memory broke. They refused to flush any data to our databases, effectively breaking our data persistence layer. I spent hours trying to reproduce or understand the problem, reading and re-reading the code. Nothing made sense. The code was largely untouched. I sat down with the team and walked them through the problem. I spoke to our Director, a seasoned developer with over 20 years of experience, and he too was stumped. I re-read the code repeatedly, even reviewing my change. Three lines to generate a hash couldn't possibly be the problem. We were so confused. I started developing conspiracy theories about what was happening, delving into the internals of the GC, looking for bugs in the JVM, you name it. Reason didn't apply, so I was now delving into the land of the impossible.</p>
<p>Eventually, we made a judgment call to contact the author of the persistent layer who had immigrated. We granted him access to the systems, and in a few hours, he found the problem and gave me a call. The first thing he opened was my three lines of code. I hadn't put a lock around the three lines of code; simplistically, it wasn't thread-safe.</p>
<h4 id="black-holes-have-a-hidden-order">4.1.2 Black Holes Have a Hidden Order</h4>
<p>When I think about black holes, I envision an unimaginable force of destruction—able to swallow planets and destroy galaxies. They are the epitome of chaos. But just like the chaos that resulted from my seemingly illogical code change, there is an actual hidden order. A system of dysfunction still based on the realities and physics of our world.</p>
<p>If we were physicists studying black holes, how would we even begin to understand them? How could we think about their nature and design, and more so, if their singularity collapses into infinity, how can we even think about its effects, draw theories, and conclusions? How do we reason about them? But even chaos has a hidden order. And we don't have to make up new rules to govern our understanding; special and general relativity are sufficient. In fact, this problem was solved earlier. Let's revisit our Penrose Diagram.</p>
<h4 id="penrose-diagrams">4.1.3 Penrose Diagrams</h4>
<p><img src="images/penrose.jpg" alt="Penrose" /></p>
<p>Penrose diagrams assist in understanding the causal structure of black holes and are a powerful tool in theoretical physics. They simplify the infinite regions, visualize the causal structure, analyze interior regions, study black hole dynamics, and help understand global properties.</p>
<p><img src="images/mercator.jpg" alt="Mercator" /></p>
<p>What are Penrose diagrams? Well their like mercator projections. You know the picture of the continents. As you know, they have several incorrect distortions, one of which is large land masses stretched out at the poles. Why is this done? To preserve the angles for navigation. So to the Penrose diagrams are able to take the complexity of blackholes and provide insights around it's causal structure, it's infinite regions and much more. If you review the diagram, you will see, on a finite space, it collapses infinity. It creates an infinite future vertically, a infinite past at the bottom, infinite space that moves from right to left.</p>
<h4 id="even-blackholes-have-a-hidden-order">4.1.4 Even Blackholes have a hidden order</h4>
<p>Referring back to my experience with those simple 3 lines of code that caused disaster. There was an order to the chaos that initially looked in-comprehensible. As we look at blackholes, despite physicists continual struggle to understand it's chaos, in roads have been made with leaps by Sir Roger Penrose to push the field forward with Penrose Diagrams. In all this, and even in our own lives, there is a pattern of taking the realities and constraints of what we know, and applying it to the unknown. We shouldn't start with chaos, with the unknowns, but start from the realities of what we do know slowly breaking down and navigating the chaos. To every chaos, there is an order. A system, and it's not beyond the realms of our reality.</p>
<p>&quot;No problem can withstand the assault of sustained thinking&quot;</p>
<h2 id="chaos-with-soft-skills">5. Chaos with Soft Skills</h2>
<h3 id="lesson-dont-be-afraid-of-chaos">5.1 Lesson: Don't be afraid of chaos</h3>
<p><img src="images/hawking.jpg" alt="Hawking" /></p>
<h3 id="a-brief-history-of-time">5.1.1 A Brief History of Time</h3>
<p>This is not so much about black holes but a lesson in one of the most intriguing theories surrounding them, proposed by Stephen Hawking in 1974. Hawking Radiation predicts that black holes decay, combining two previously separate realms of physics: Quantum Mechanics and General Relativity.</p>
<p>However, not long ago, there was an article on Forbes where another PhD physicist completely dismantled the theory. Since then, there has been much debate about its correctness and legitimacy. Some even say that Hawking Radiation is nothing more than a theory or narrative Hawking put together as a way to help readers of his book &quot;A Brief History of Time&quot; understand black holes better, suggesting that real physicists know the truth.</p>
<h3 id="lesson">5.1.2 Lesson</h3>
<p>Regardless of the debate, Stephen Hawking took a bold step in putting forward this theory. Remember, he released this along with his book &quot;A Brief History of Time&quot; in 1974, when there was no internet or large language models, and black hole theory was significantly less advanced. He knew it was controversial because it challenged established views around general relativity and quantum mechanics. Whether to be hailed as an Einstein or much later an idiot, he put forth his theory.</p>
<p>Often, as technical people, ideas, potential solutions, and designs may be lost because of what is established and a lack of belief or confidence. Solutions should be judged on their merit and put forth with conviction. They should not be lost because we fear what is, or are enveloped by a lack of confidence in our own insights.</p>
<p>“True innovation often requires the courage to challenge the impossible. Embrace your ideas and let them shine, for they may shape the future.”</p>
<h2 id="chaos-in-life">6. Chaos in Life</h2>
<h3 id="life-through-the-lens-of-your-chaos">6.1 Life through the lens of your chaos</h3>
<p><img src="images/batman.jpg" alt="Batman" /></p>
<h3 id="hosting-company-experience">6.1.1 Hosting Company Experience</h3>
<p>I joined a hosting company with great expectations. In fact, the architect took a liking to me and believed I could help him transform the business to a service-oriented architecture or TOGAF. Unfortunately, instead of collaborating with others and him, I tried to solve difficult problems alone, thinking I alone was sufficient for success. My efforts soon led him to incorrectly micro-manage me, and our relationship started to deteriorate. He had his own personal demons, and I wasn't helping, and soon he tried to force me out of the company. I feared him. Thankfully, I was offered a rotation to another team. Eventually, despite his best efforts to transform the organization, he ended up leaving. But that's not where the story ends. It ends with me struggling to escape the darkness of that experience. I was so hurt, I felt so incompetent, and in every interaction in that organization, I applied that lens. I felt everyone around me thought I was a fraud, useless and ill-equipped. Reaching this epiphany took a bit of work, but the place I was in was dark like a black hole; that one event caused an infinite collapse, further and further into darkness.</p>
<h3 id="lesson-1">6.1.2 Lesson</h3>
<p>A black hole is a dark unknown. Its event horizon is the first contact with its power and destruction. As mentioned when we covered spaghettification, on entry, there is no escape. No information escapes, not even light itself. Its darkness is all-encompassing. Today, you may be faced with a similar challenge or have been through one. The darkness can be overwhelming. Some event or situation has marred your ability to function optimally. Some set of circumstances has damaged your brand, reputation, or confidence in yourself.</p>
<p>My advice to you is, don't be scared of the dark. Sometimes you may try your best to push against the inevitability of the event horizon. It's an impossible task. Light and information never escape. All that's left is to push through the darkness, accept what is, learn from it what you can, and follow the infinite. Don't allow the lens of past experiences, pain, or darkness to destroy today.</p>
<p>Embrace the dark, and rise up. Deshi Basara, Deshi Basara!</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C4 Level Diagrams &amp; Git</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/wiltw-8.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/wiltw-8.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>creative</category>
      <category>wiltw</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="uml-diagrams-from-typescript">UML Diagrams from Typescript</h1>
<p>I was recently putting together <a href="https://c4model.com/">C4 Model diagrams</a> and when I got to the last-level, I needed code level-views.
This is where I stumbled onto the following automation to assist with TypeScript to UML.
Automatic generation of UML from typrscript.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/demike/TsUML2">TsUML2</a></p>
<p>There is also a good option for C# users:</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/dotMorten/DotNetOMDGenerator">Generate OMD</a></p>
<h1 id="git-editorconfig-and-darn-windows-users">Git, EditorConfig and Darn Windows Users</h1>
<p>If you in a team and the only Linux/Mac user and using Git. This is the setting you need for you git config.</p>
<pre><code>core.autocrlf=false
</code></pre>
<h1 id="git-access-multiple-accounts">Git access multiple accounts</h1>
<p>Adapt this and add to your ~/.ssh/config</p>
<pre><code class="language-yaml"># Enterprise account
Host github.com-enterprise
  HostName github.com
  User git
  IdentityFile ~/.ssh/id_rsa_github_enterprise
  IdentitiesOnly yes

# Personal account
Host github.com-personal
  HostName github.com
  User git
  IdentityFile ~/.ssh/id_rsa_github_personal
  IdentitiesOnly yes
</code></pre>
<p>Make sure for each repo you set the following to match:</p>
<pre><code class="language-sh">git config user.name &quot;Your Enterprise Username&quot;
git config user.email &quot;your_enterprise_email@example.com&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>Then define your remote origin:</p>
<pre><code>git remote set-url origin git@github.com-enterprise:Organization/repo.git
</code></pre>
<h1 id="high-fidelity-tests">High Fidelity Tests</h1>
<p>This is an absolutely well articulated blog post on Testing.
It emphasizes to pursue high fidelity tests. That is tests, that are closest to reality.
It suggested a three-fold approach, of starting with (1) use the real thing (2) use a fake, and worst-case (3) use a mock.</p>
<p>I find this salient advice, tying directly to my experience.</p>
<p><a href="https://testing.googleblog.com/2024/02/increase-test-fidelity-by-avoiding-mocks.html">Read it here</a></p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Github Dependabot API &amp; Dumpify</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/wiltw-9.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/wiltw-9.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>creative</category>
      <category>wiltw</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h2 id="using-dumpify-for-neovim-debugging-in-c">Using Dumpify for Neovim debugging in C#</h2>
<p>This is a great aid if you looking to get insight into debug information via console, while not using a debugger. DAP sucks.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/MoaidHathot/Dumpify">Dumpify</a></p>
<h2 id="retrieving-dependadot-alerts-from-github-api">Retrieving dependadot alerts from Github API</h2>
<pre><code class="language-python">import csv
import requests

OWNER = 'your_owner_name'  # GitHub Owner name
REPOSITORIES = ['repo1', 'repo2']  # List of repositories
PAT = 'your_personal_access_token'  # GitHub Personal Access Token
CSV_FILE = 'dependabot_alerts.csv'  # Output CSV file name

session = requests.Session()
session.headers.update({
    &quot;Accept&quot;: &quot;application/vnd.github+json&quot;,
    &quot;Authorization&quot;: f&quot;Bearer {PAT}&quot;,
    &quot;X-GitHub-Api-Version&quot;: &quot;2022-11-28&quot;
})

def fetch_dependabot_alerts(owner, repo):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Fetch Dependabot alerts for a specific repository using the session.&quot;&quot;&quot;
    url = f&quot;https://api.github.com/repos/{owner}/{repo}/dependabot/alerts?state=open&amp;severity=critical&amp;per_page=100&quot;
    response = session.get(url)
    if response.status_code == 200:
        return response.json()
    else:
        print(f&quot;Failed to fetch alerts for {repo}: {response.status_code}&quot;)
        return []

def process_alerts(alerts, repo):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Process each alert to extract relevant fields, including the repository name.&quot;&quot;&quot;
    processed_alerts = []
    for alert in alerts:
        processed_alert = {
            &quot;repository&quot;: repo,
            &quot;number&quot;: alert.get(&quot;number&quot;),
            &quot;state&quot;: alert.get(&quot;state&quot;),
            &quot;dependency_ecosystem&quot;: alert.get(&quot;dependency&quot;, {}).get(&quot;package&quot;, {}).get(&quot;ecosystem&quot;, &quot;&quot;),
            &quot;dependency_name&quot;: alert.get(&quot;dependency&quot;, {}).get(&quot;package&quot;, {}).get(&quot;name&quot;, &quot;&quot;),
            &quot;security_advisory_description&quot;: alert.get(&quot;security_advisory&quot;, {}).get(&quot;description&quot;, &quot;&quot;)
        }
        processed_alerts.append(processed_alert)
    return processed_alerts

def write_to_csv(data):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Write the processed alert data to a CSV file.&quot;&quot;&quot;
    with open(CSV_FILE, mode='w', newline='') as file:
        writer = csv.DictWriter(file, fieldnames=data[0].keys())
        writer.writeheader()
        for row in data:
            writer.writerow(row)

def main():
    &quot;&quot;&quot;Main function to orchestrate the fetching, processing, and writing of Dependabot alert data.&quot;&quot;&quot;
    all_alerts = []
    for repo in REPOSITORIES:
        alerts = fetch_dependabot_alerts(OWNER, repo)
        if alerts:
            processed_alerts = process_alerts(alerts, repo)
            all_alerts.extend(processed_alerts)
    if all_alerts:
        write_to_csv(all_alerts)
        print(f&quot;Data written to {CSV_FILE}&quot;)
    else:
        print(&quot;No data to write.&quot;)

if __name__ == &quot;__main__&quot;:
    main()


</code></pre>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InnerSource. SPACE. DORA. DEVEX.</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/wiltw-10.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/wiltw-10.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>creative</category>
      <category>wiltw</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h2 id="query-agic-rules-service-endpoints">Query AGIC rules (service endpoints)</h2>
<h3 id="query-the-data">Query the data</h3>
<pre><code class="language-sh"> kubectl --kubeconfig ~/.kube/my-config get ingress --all-namespaces -o json &gt; ingresses.json
</code></pre>
<h3 id="pretty-print">Pretty Print</h3>
<pre><code class="language-sh">cat ingresses.json | jq -r '
.items[] |
{
  namespace: .metadata.namespace,
  name: .metadata.name,
  rules: .spec.rules[]
} |
&quot;Ingress Name: \(.name),Host: \(.rules.host),Paths: \(.rules.http.paths[] | &quot;Path: \(.path), Service Name: \(.backend.service.name), Service Port: \(.backend.service.port.number)&quot;)&quot;'
</code></pre>
<h2 id="innersource">InnerSource</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>What is InnerSource?
Simplistically it's nothing more then when a company tries to do open-source but in a closed space.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tfPhkZ87bEY">3 minute video I found helpful</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>InnerSource is enabled by tools and processes, but it is also a change
to the culture. The biggest change is allowing mistakes, talking
about them, and learning from them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="innersource.png" alt="alt text" /></p>
<h2 id="dora-vs-space-vs-devex">DORA vs SPACE vs DEVEX</h2>
<p>I found this really great analogy:</p>
<p><img src="Compare.jpg" alt="Linked" /></p>
<h2 id="raci-matrix">RACI Matrix</h2>
<p>A RACI chart, also called a RACI matrix, is a type of responsibility assignment matrix (RAM) in project management. In
practice, it’s a simple spreadsheet or table that lists all stakeholders on a project and their level involvement in
each task, denoted with the letters R, A, C or I. Once these roles are defined, assignments can be attributed to the
roles and work can begin.</p>
<p>R, A, C, I stands for:</p>
<p>Responsible
Accountable
Consulted
Informed</p>
<p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/advisor/business/raci-chart/#What_Is_A_Raci_Chart?">Forbes Link</a></p>
<h2 id="team-topologies">Team Topologies</h2>
<h4 id="team-topologies-overview">1. Team Topologies Overview</h4>
<p>Team Topologies, as described by Matthew Skelton and Manuel Pais in their book “Team Topologies,” focuses on optimizing
team interactions and alignments with business goals. The core team types and interaction modes are key concepts in this
framework.</p>
<h4 id="core-team-types">2. Core Team Types</h4>
<p><strong>a. Stream-Aligned Teams</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Definition</strong>: Teams aligned to a flow of work from a segment of the business domain.
• <strong>Purpose</strong>: Delivering valuable increments of work to end-users continuously.
• <strong>Example</strong>: A team dedicated to a specific product feature, such as the user onboarding process or payment gateway.</p>
<p><strong>b. Enabling Teams</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Definition</strong>: Teams that assist other teams to overcome obstacles and adopt new technologies or practices.
• <strong>Purpose</strong>: Providing specialized knowledge and facilitating the adoption of best practices.
• <strong>Example</strong>: A team focused on helping other teams implement CI/CD pipelines or adopt cloud technologies.</p>
<p><strong>c. Complicated-Subsystem Teams</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Definition</strong>: Teams responsible for building and maintaining complex subsystems that require specialized knowledge.
• <strong>Purpose</strong>: Handling parts of the system that require deep expertise and cannot be easily managed by stream-aligned
teams.
• <strong>Example</strong>: A team dedicated to developing a high-performance database engine or a sophisticated machine learning
model.</p>
<p><strong>d. Platform Teams</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Definition</strong>: Teams that build and maintain platforms used by other teams to deliver work.
• <strong>Purpose</strong>: Providing self-service APIs, tools, and services to enable other teams to deliver software efficiently.
• <strong>Example</strong>: A team managing the internal cloud infrastructure, CI/CD tools, or authentication services.</p>
<h4 id="interaction-modes">3. Interaction Modes</h4>
<p><strong>a. Collaboration</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Description</strong>: Teams work together for a defined period to achieve a specific outcome.
• <strong>Use Case</strong>: When multiple teams need to work together to deliver a complex feature that spans different domains.</p>
<p><strong>b. X-as-a-Service</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Description</strong>: One team provides a service that other teams can consume independently.
• <strong>Use Case</strong>: Platform teams offering CI/CD pipelines as a service to stream-aligned teams.</p>
<p><strong>c. Facilitating</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Description</strong>: Enabling teams facilitate and assist other teams to overcome specific challenges.
• <strong>Use Case</strong>: An enabling team helping a stream-aligned team adopt a new testing framework.</p>
<h4 id="common-practices-for-organizing-delivery-teams">4. Common Practices for Organizing Delivery Teams</h4>
<p><strong>a. Define Clear Team Boundaries and Responsibilities</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Clarity</strong>: Ensure each team has a clear mission and well-defined responsibilities to avoid overlaps and confusion.
• <strong>Autonomy</strong>: Empower teams to make decisions within their domain to increase accountability and efficiency.</p>
<p><strong>b. Optimize for Flow</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Stream Alignment</strong>: Align teams to the flow of work that delivers value to customers. Avoid organizing teams around
rigid component boundaries.
• <strong>Value Streams</strong>: Identify and organize around value streams to ensure teams can deliver end-to-end features.</p>
<p><strong>c. Promote Cross-Functional Collaboration</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Skills Diversity</strong>: Ensure teams have the necessary skills to deliver complete solutions, including development, QA,
UX, and operations.
• <strong>Collaboration Tools</strong>: Use tools and practices that facilitate seamless communication and collaboration, such as
agile boards, chat platforms, and video conferencing.</p>
<p><strong>d. Facilitate Continuous Improvement</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Feedback Loops</strong>: Establish regular feedback loops through retrospectives, reviews, and one-on-one meetings to
identify areas for improvement.
• <strong>Learning Culture</strong>: Encourage continuous learning and improvement by providing access to training, conferences, and
knowledge-sharing sessions.</p>
<p><strong>e. Balance Stability and Innovation</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Stable Base</strong>: Maintain a stable platform and set of practices for the majority of the work while allowing for
innovation and experimentation in a controlled manner.
• <strong>Innovation Time</strong>: Allocate time for teams to explore new ideas and technologies that can drive future improvements.</p>
<h4 id="practical-implementation-tips">5. Practical Implementation Tips</h4>
<p><strong>a. Start Small and Scale Gradually</strong></p>
<p>• Pilot new team structures with a small group before scaling across the organization.
• Gather feedback and adjust based on what works and what doesn’t.</p>
<p><strong>b. Use Metrics to Guide Decisions</strong></p>
<p>• Measure team performance using relevant metrics such as lead time, deployment frequency, and defect rates.
• Use these metrics to identify bottlenecks and areas for improvement.</p>
<p><strong>c. Encourage Ownership and Accountability</strong></p>
<p>• Foster a sense of ownership by allowing teams to take full responsibility for their services or components.
• Implement practices like DevOps where teams are responsible for both development and operations.</p>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong>
Organizing delivery teams effectively requires a thoughtful approach that aligns with business goals and fosters
collaboration, autonomy, and continuous improvement. By leveraging the principles of Team Topologies, organizations can
create an environment where teams are empowered to deliver high-quality software efficiently and adapt to changing
needs.</p>
<h2 id="what-to-do-if-you-blank-in-an-interview">What to do if you blank in an interview?</h2>
<p>It’s natural to occasionally lose your train of thought or feel flustered during an interview. Here’s a structured
approach to handle such situations gracefully:</p>
<p><strong>1. Pause and Take a Breath</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Stay Calm</strong>: Take a deep breath to calm your nerves. It’s okay to take a moment to collect your thoughts.
• <strong>Pause</strong>: Use a brief pause to compose yourself. This can also give the impression that you are considering your
answer carefully.</p>
<p><strong>2. Ask for Clarification</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Clarify the Question</strong>: If you’re uncertain about the question, politely ask the interviewer to repeat or clarify
it. This can give you additional time to think and ensure you’re addressing the right topic.
• Example: “Could you please repeat the question? I want to make sure I address it correctly.”</p>
<p><strong>3. Acknowledge and Redirect</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Acknowledge the Pause</strong>: If you’ve forgotten your point mid-answer, acknowledge it briefly and redirect the
conversation.
• Example: “I apologize, I seem to have lost my train of thought. Let me start again.”
• <strong>Restart or Pivot</strong>: Either restart your answer or pivot to a related point that you can speak about confidently.</p>
<p><strong>4. Use Filler Phrases</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Filler Phrases</strong>: Use phrases like “That’s a great question” or “Let me think about that for a moment” to buy
yourself a few seconds to regain your composure.
• Example: “That’s a great question. I think the key point here is…”</p>
<p><strong>5. Summarize and Simplify</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Summarize Your Key Points</strong>: If you’re struggling with a detailed response, summarize your key points and then
expand on them.
• Example: “In summary, my approach would focus on collaboration, continuous improvement, and leveraging best practices.
To elaborate…”</p>
<p><strong>6. Be Honest</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Admit if You Don’t Know</strong>: If you genuinely don’t know the answer, it’s better to admit it than to fumble through an
uncertain response.
• Example: “I’m not sure about the exact details, but I would approach it by doing XYZ…”</p>
<p><strong>7. Offer to Follow Up</strong></p>
<p>• <strong>Follow-Up</strong>: If applicable, offer to follow up with a more detailed answer after the interview.
• Example: “I don’t have the exact information on hand, but I’d be happy to follow up with a detailed response after the
interview.”</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Story Telling, BDD</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/wiltw-7.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/wiltw-7.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>creative</category>
      <category>wiltw</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-power-of-story-telling">The Power of Story Telling</h2>
<p>It allows an organization to remember.
It is easier to remember that which is tied to emotion then that which is pure fact.
Speak in stories.</p>
<p><a href="https://boz.com/articles/speak-in-stories">Speak In Stories</a></p>
<h2 id="the-power-of-behaviour-driven-development">The Power of Behaviour Driven Development</h2>
<p>Testing meets story-telling in BDD.</p>
<ol>
<li>TDD vs BDD</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="/images/BDD1.png" alt="TDD vs BDD" /></p>
<ol start="2">
<li>BDD is about Communication</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="/images/BDD2.png" alt="Communication" /></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>BDD is about shared understanding</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="/images/BDD3.png" alt="Shared Understanding" /></p>
<ol start="4">
<li>BDD is another shift left</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="/images/BDD4.png" alt="Shift Left" /></p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Build your own AI code-reviewer</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/ai-code-reviewer.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/ai-code-reviewer.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>tech</category>
      <category>diy</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/copilot.jpg" alt="CoPilot" /></p>
<h2 id="build-your-own-ai-code-reviewer">Build Your Own AI Code-Reviewer</h2>
<p>In this journey, I embarked on creating a plugin for my IDE, designed to highlight code snippets and provide insights on their function, quality improvement, and refactoring potential.</p>
<h3 id="why-build-your-own">Why Build Your Own?</h3>
<p>Here are compelling reasons to consider:</p>
<ol>
<li>A local LLM (Large Language Model) guarantees your privacy.</li>
<li>The absence of a suitable plugin for your specific IDE.</li>
<li>Desire to customize the LLM's role and focus.</li>
<li>Interest in leveraging open-source LLMs for experimentation.</li>
<li>Curiosity to explore various LLMs.</li>
</ol>
<p>If these resonate with you, prepare for a rewarding endeavor!</p>
<h3 id="the-steps-involved">The Steps Involved</h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Choosing the Right LLM</strong></li>
<li><strong>Setting Up the LLM</strong></li>
<li><strong>Mastering LLM Interactions</strong></li>
<li><strong>Crafting Your IDE Plugin</strong></li>
<li><strong>Refining the Outcome</strong></li>
</ol>
<h3 id="choosing-the-right-llm">Choosing the Right LLM</h3>
<p>Limited by my hardware, I sought LLMs that were compact, efficient, and specialized in coding. I discovered a helpful list by <a href="https://github.com/continuedev/what-llm-to-use">continuedev</a> and chose <a href="https://deepseek.com/">Deepseek Coder</a>.</p>
<h3 id="setting-up-the-llm">Setting Up the LLM</h3>
<p>My go-to was <a href="https://lmstudio.ai/">LM Studio</a>. Keep these points in mind:</p>
<ul>
<li>LLMs come in Base and Instruct types: Base excels in completing code, while Instruct is adept at writing from scratch.</li>
<li><a href="https://lmstudio.ai/quantization">Quantization</a> affects the LLM's performance, balancing inference quality, speed, and resource usage.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Tip: For a 7B model, a q4_K_S quantization is recommended.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="interacting-with-the-llm">Interacting with the LLM</h3>
<p>LM Studio facilitates interactions similarly to the OpenAI API. Here's a sample interaction using curl or <a href="https://httpie.io">Httpie</a>:</p>
<pre><code class="language-json">{ 
  &quot;messages&quot;: [ 
    { &quot;role&quot;: &quot;system&quot;, &quot;content&quot;: &quot;Review my code as an expert senior developer. Be critical. Focus on readability and maintainability. Refactor if needed.&quot; },
    { &quot;role&quot;: &quot;user&quot;, &quot;content&quot;: &lt;code snippet&gt; }
  ], 
  &quot;temperature&quot;: 0.7, 
  &quot;max_tokens&quot;: -1,
  &quot;stream&quot;: false
}
</code></pre>
<p>Define the LLM's behavior as 'system' and input your code snippets as 'user'.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Note: Code must be properly escaped for POST HTTP requests.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="building-your-ide-plugin">Building Your IDE Plugin</h3>
<p>I developed a plugin for LazyVim using <a href="https://neovim.io">neovim</a>. Here's the process:</p>
<ul>
<li>Initialize your plugin on GitHub.</li>
<li>Start with a simple echo function.</li>
<li>Install the plugin in LazyVim (<code>~/.config/nvim/lua/plugins/</code>).</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-lua"># reviewer.lua
return {
  {
    &quot;daneb/reviewer.nvim&quot;,
  },
}
</code></pre>
<ul>
<li>Enhance the plugin functionality (see <a href="https://github.com/daneb/reviewer.nvim">Reviewer.nvim</a>).</li>
<li>Use LazyVim to sync plugin updates.</li>
<li>Implement keymapping (located in <code>~/.config/nvim/lua/config/keymaps.lua</code>).</li>
</ul>
<pre><code class="language-lua">vim.api.nvim_set_keymap(
  &quot;v&quot;,
  &quot;&lt;leader&gt;lm&quot;,
  ':lua require(&quot;reviewer&quot;).main_function()&lt;CR&gt;',
  { noremap = true, silent = true, desc = &quot;AI Reviewer&quot; }
)
</code></pre>
<h3 id="tweaking-the-result">Tweaking the Result</h3>
<p><img src="/images/reviewer.jpg" alt="Result" /></p>
<p>Your plugin, now functional in your IDE, can be aesthetically enhanced with features like window sizing, colors, and borders.</p>
<p>Challenges remain, such as ensuring proper code snippet escape, particularly with regex. Initially, I used a curl call instead of the built-in neovim HTTP API.</p>
<p>It's a work in progress, but it's an accessible, enjoyable, and fulfilling project!</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2024 Reading List</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/2024-reading.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/2024-reading.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 08:16:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>creative</category>
      <category>reading</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/library.jpg" alt="2024 Reading List" /></p>
<h2 id="currently-reading">Currently Reading</h2>
<ol start="2">
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/boilerplate/Refactoring.html">Refactoring - Martin Fowler</a></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="read">Read</h2>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Atlas-Management-Thinking-Edward-Bono-ebook/dp/B01MF6ANHI/ref=sr_1_1?crid=1K9QDZ8HPD6HU&amp;keywords=atlas+of+management+thinking&amp;qid=1705258470&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=atlas+of+management%2Cstripbooks-intl-ship%2C300&amp;sr=1-1">Atlas of Management Thinking - Edward De Bono</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Radical-Candor-KIM-SCOTT/dp/1509845380/ref=sr_1_2?crid=12ZKWI70B0RL5&amp;keywords=radical+candor&amp;qid=1705258557&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=radical+cando%2Cstripbooks-intl-ship%2C287&amp;sr=1-2">Radical Candour - Kim Scott</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10784.The_Lion_The_Witch_And_The_Wardrobe">The Lion, The Witch, and The Wardrobe - C.S. Lewis</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Think-Again-Power-Knowing-What/dp/1984878107">Think Again - Adam Grant</a></li>
<li><a href="">The Fellowship of the Rings - JRR Tolkien</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10133624-black-holes">Black Holes - The key to understanding the Universe</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Think-Like-Software-Engineering-Manager/dp/1633438430/ref=cm_cr_arp_d_product_top?ie=UTF8">Think Like an Engineering Manager</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Are-Your-Lights-Figure-Problem/dp/0932633161">Are your lights on? - Gerald Weinberg</a></li>
<li><a href="https://livebook.manning.com/book/automate-everyday-work-tasks-with-chatgpt/">Elevate Your Productivity: Automate Everyday Work Tasks with ChatGPT</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Tidy-First-Kent-Beck-ebook/dp/B0CL7ZMLWH?crid=8HK9HS1B8F2M&amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.kgF7tsQPvYl47LL64DcX0OX3MEJL6K9rhHU8UI5C_ONJ--Jw2e14BzNsinzOLaC0Q2H-hEmajOrHmdHlqUK66xsIpnHjTFSE08NNjC_ia0HdcZfAR6RZWRYIhtcYjT2UZBiMU9arJ0Q7l0c5oQ9rl-Ultledcr-DfSMB5iaVeo3vNWOen8f-YytyjnQNWFNNXa4b5lSPSuDLmW4fsv-qR-oJmoBZyAAKWuarKHvdmkw.GGK58Zb_YAg9_WBxmpnC3c5xObu0REr8WUw-Ivd8kh4&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;keywords=tidy+first&amp;qid=1728289492&amp;sprefix=tidy+first,aps,397&amp;sr=8-1">Tidy First - Kent Beck</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1492043451/?bestFormat=true&amp;k=fundamentals%20of%20software%20architecture&amp;crid=3I3HWUVCWW81N&amp;sprefix=fundamentals%20archite">Fundamentals of Software Architecture: An Engineering Approach</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Daniel-Commentary-Bible-Believers-ebook/dp/B01N6F478T?crid=1AQ8T6AMNJUY9&amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.HsV_4HaLfMCQZudhHKogg04fYUhefefur0DCcehY1_87jFZbYhNJ39vcUUu3SqcM.miYzJLqtVEGULdm89ve2WnmmpRI6jQgV8g55g1XS0oQ&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;keywords=daniel+dr.ruckman&amp;qid=1732263911&amp;sprefix=daniel+dr.ruckman,aps,293&amp;sr=8-1">The Book of Daniel - Dr. Ruckman</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Secrets-Consulting-Gerald-M-Weinberg/dp/0932633013">The Secrets of Consulting Vol 1</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Book-Three-Prydain-Chronicles/dp/0805080481">The Book of Three - Lloyd Alexandar</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Things-Architect-Knows-Transformation-Pragmatic/dp/1680502887">37 Things one architect knows about IT Transformation - Gregor Hohpe</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Worst-Class-Trip-Ever/dp/1484708497">The Worst Class Trip ever - Dave Barry</a></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="planned">Planned</h2>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://craftinginterpreters.com/">Robert Nystrom - Crafting Intepreters</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15842786-understanding-computation">Tom Stuart - Understanding Computation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://geraldmweinberg.com/Site/QSM_vol_1.html">Gerald Weinberg - Quality Software Management, Vol 1: Systems Thinking</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Thinking-Systems-Donella-H-Meadows/dp/1603580557">Donella Meadows - Thinking in Systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1491983647?tag=bbookshub-20&amp;linkCode=ogi&amp;th=1&amp;psc=1">Brendan Burns - Designing Distributed Systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.larkinestate.com/books/dispensational-truth.html">Clarence Larking - Dispensational Truth</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Betsy Beyer - Site Reliability Engineering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bookshop.org/books/rationality-what-it-is-why-it-seems-scarce-why-it-matters/9780525561996">Steven Pinker - Rationality: What It Is, Why It Seems Scarce, Why It Matter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Lies-My-Govt-Told-Me-ebook/dp/B09R4Y6YKJ/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=lies+my+government+told+me+robert+malone&amp;qid=1673239997&amp;s=digital-text&amp;sprefix=lies%2Cdigital-text%2C455&amp;sr=1-1">Lies My Gov't Told Me: And the Better Future Coming</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B09PZ9X17W/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_d_asin_title_o00?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">Traced: Human DNA's Big Surprise</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Accelerate-Software-Performing-Technology-Organizations-ebook/dp/B07B9F83WM">Jez-Humble, Gene Kim - Accelerate: The Science of Lean Software and DevOps: Building and Scaling High Performing Technology Organizations</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.brendangregg.com/blog/2020-07-15/systems-performance-2nd-edition.html">Brendan Gregg - Systems Performance</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Site Reliability Engineering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sre.google/books/">Building secure &amp; reliable systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/building-evolutionary-architectures/9781492097532/">Neal Ford, Rebecca Parsons - Building Evolutionary Architectures</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hard-Thing-About-Things-Building/dp/0062273205">The Hard Thing About Hard Things - Ben Horowitz</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-General-Systems-Thinking-ebook/dp/B004VS9AUS/?_encoding=UTF8&amp;pd_rd_w=ceglc&amp;content-id=amzn1.sym.cf86ec3a-68a6-43e9-8115-04171136930a&amp;pf_rd_p=cf86ec3a-68a6-43e9-8115-04171136930a&amp;pf_rd_r=138-2750200-6069238&amp;pd_rd_wg=RcZwU&amp;pd_rd_r=680c1234-d2b8-45bc-a398-8acb35ad454c&amp;ref_=aufs_ap_sc_dsk">Introduction to General Systems Thinking - Gerald Weinberg</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Return-God-Hypothesis-Compelling-Scientific/dp/0062071505">Return of the God Hypothesis - Dr. Stephen Meyer</a></li>
</ol>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Build your own static web site generator</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/static-website-gen.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/static-website-gen.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>tech</category>
      <category>diy</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/happyfrogger.jpg" alt="HappyFrogger" /></p>
<h1 id="how-i-built-my-own-static-site-generator-for-a-personal-blog">How I Built My Own Static Site Generator for a Personal Blog</h1>
<p>In the ever-evolving landscape of web development, the allure of simplicity often leads to innovative solutions. This
was precisely my experience as I ventured into creating my own static site generator for my personal blog. It definitely
doesn't have everything, but it's enough, done across 2 days and is only 132 lines of C#. Here’s
a <a href="https://github.com/daneb/happyfrogger">glimpse into my journey</a>, offering insights and practical steps that might
inspire your own custom project.</p>
<h2 id="step-1-embracing-markdown-and-c-for-content-and-processing">Step 1: Embracing Markdown and C# for Content and Processing</h2>
<p>The cornerstone of my project was the utilization of Markdown for content creation, chosen for its simplicity and
flexibility. Coupled with C#, a language I was already comfortable with, I used the <code>Markdig</code> library to process
Markdown files into HTML. This setup provided a straightforward way to write and transform blog content.</p>
<h2 id="step-2-implementing-templating-with-razor">Step 2: Implementing Templating with Razor</h2>
<p>Consistency in appearance is key to any blog's identity. Leveraging the power of the Razor templating engine, commonly
used in ASP.NET, I could craft dynamic templates. These templates ensured a uniform layout and style across various blog
posts, embedding the essence of the blog’s personality into every page.</p>
<h2 id="step-3-styling-with-tailwind-css">Step 3: Styling with Tailwind CSS</h2>
<p>Aesthetic appeal and responsive design are non-negotiable in today’s web. Tailwind CSS was my choice for its
utility-first approach, enabling me to elegantly style the blog. The integration of Tailwind CSS guaranteed not only
functionality but also visual appeal, ensuring the blog's seamless presentation on diverse devices.</p>
<h2 id="step-4-front-matter-parsing-with-yamldotnet">Step 4: Front Matter Parsing with YamlDotNet</h2>
<p>A crucial feature for any blog is the ability to categorize and manage metadata for each post. YamlDotNet came to the
rescue, allowing me to parse Front Matter in Markdown files. This addition enabled me to define properties like title,
date, and categories directly within the Markdown, greatly enhancing content manageability and organization.</p>
<h2 id="step-5-embedding-github-gists">Step 5: Embedding GitHub Gists</h2>
<p>To enrich the technical aspect of the blog, embedding code snippets was essential. GitHub Gists provided a simple yet
effective way to incorporate these snippets. By placing placeholders in the Markdown content, which were later replaced
with Gist embed codes during HTML generation, I could seamlessly integrate dynamic code examples into the posts.</p>
<h2 id="step-6-deployment-on-github-pages">Step 6: Deployment on GitHub Pages</h2>
<p>The final piece of the puzzle was deploying the blog. GitHub Pages offered an efficient and straightforward hosting
solution. After setting up a repository and configuring the GitHub Pages settings, I pushed the static HTML files,
bringing the blog to life on the web.</p>
<h2 id="overcoming-challenges">Overcoming Challenges</h2>
<p>The journey wasn’t without its challenges. Ensuring that Tailwind CSS properly styled the dynamically generated HTML
content required some tweaking, solved by configuring the JIT Compiler and the correct loading sequence. Deploying the
site with a custom domain on GitHub Pages needed careful DNS configuration and repository setup, including a <code>.nojekyll</code>
file to bypass Jekyll processing.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Crafting a static site generator from scratch was not only immensely satisfying but also provided a tailor-made solution
for my blogging needs. It allowed complete control over the design, functionality, and content, resulting in a unique
and personal blogging platform. For those inspired to embark on a similar endeavor, remember to keep things simple,
leverage familiar tools, and enjoy the creative process. Your perfect blogging platform might just be a few code lines
away.</p>
<p>Happy coding and blogging!</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Behold the Lamb of God</title>
      <link>https://danebalia.com/behold-the-lamb.html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://danebalia.com/behold-the-lamb.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 22:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <category>faith</category>
      <category>sermon</category>
      <author>Dane Balia</author>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/lamb.jpg" alt="Behold the Lamb" /></p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Good morning brothers and sisters.
If we reflect on the period or time of Covid, we consider it was a  scary and dark time for us all. A time when people where in search of answers. For some this was science, but sadly science became the control of governments to dictate their narratives and propagate their outcomes. Studies once reliable were shown to be easily polluted, easily accepted and the community that were supposed to gate was thin.</p>
<p>An example was 3 people who wrote 20 hoax papers about gender-identity, group-identity and sexuality etc. 6 of their papers were rejected. 7 were under serious peer reviews and the rest were progressing to approval. Another random sample of 5000 papers in one field alone, Neuroscience, revealed 34% of papers were plagiarized or just made up in 2020.</p>
<p>During Covid we also saw a divisions in society, as there were those against vaccines and those for. People were ostracized. Society and people turned on each other. The media took sides and pushed agendas from governments right or wrong. What was clear, was that truth was relative. It was cheap. Easy to deny, easy to twist. Information was censored. People were scared. People were confused. They were looking for truth, but deceived or unable to discern truth. It was a dark time.</p>
<p>Not only where we fighting a diseases, government intervention, but there was a mindset being proliferated and that of gender-politics (still making it's rounds today). Men could call themselves women, trans individuals wanted to be called by specific pronouns, people could be whoever they wanted to be. A women could label themselves man, and a man label themselves a woman despite their clear physical design. This thinking continues today in America and now in Europe. Again, truth is not based on reality but is not defined from the figments of peoples imaginations.</p>
<p>But amidst these dark times, where truth is relative and controlled, there are some truths no man can alter.</p>
<ol>
<li>Our God is true. Basic human reasoning could tell you that.</li>
<li>And the second, the focus for the message today, The Gospel is true and is the worlds only hope.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>READ 2 Corinthians 4:1-6</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="may-blindness-be-removed">May blindness be removed</h2>
<p>This morning, that light has shone out of darkness, for today there be some seated here whose blindness has been removed. But there are also others who remind blind. Darkness is upon you, but you believe you are in the light. Be warned friend, it is easy for darkness to appear as light, when darkness is all you know. May the Lord awaken you this morning, may your eyes open, may the glorious light of the gospel shine and may it give you the light of the knowledge of the glory of God.</p>
<p>Let's turn to the Lord in prayer.</p>
<h3 id="pray-for-someone-to-get-saved.for-the-darkness-to-be-removed">Pray for someone to get saved. For the darkness to be removed</h3>
<h2 id="body">Body</h2>
<h3 id="hell-matters-are-you-going-there">1. Hell matters, are you going there?</h3>
<h4 id="hell-is-real">1.1 Hell is real</h4>
<h5 id="i.the-logical-argument">i. The logical argument</h5>
<ul>
<li>I just want to say this morning, if it's not immediately clear, hell is real.</li>
<li>Look out at the very basics mechanics and patterns of the our world.</li>
<li>There is a very definitive law embedded in all things. You reap what you sow. You sit around and do nothing and well you will be without a job. You don't study for exams and you will fail. You break the law, you are punished. Why should the fundamental mechanic be any different when it comes to eternity when this is our reality?</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="ii.the-biblical-evidence">ii. The biblical evidence</h5>
<ul>
<li>But perhaps if the logical argument doesn't suffice how about the truth, accuracy and reliability of scripture. There are 54 verses in scripture that tell us of hell (Deut 32:22, Isa 5:14, Luke 12:5, 2 Peter 2:4).</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Deu 32:22  For a fire is kindled in mine anger, and shall burn unto the lowest hell, and shall consume the earth with her increase, and set on fire the foundations of the mountains.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Isa 5:14  Therefore hell hath enlarged herself, and opened her mouth without measure: and their glory, and their multitude, and their pomp, and he that rejoiceth, shall descend into it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Luk 12:5  But I will forewarn you whom ye shall fear: Fear him, which after he hath killed hath power to cast into hell; yea, I say unto you, Fear him.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>2Pe 2:4  For if God spared not the angels that sinned, but cast them down to hell, and delivered them into chains of darkness, to be reserved unto judgment;</p>
</blockquote>
<h5 id="iii.call-out-the-guilty">iii. Call out the guilty</h5>
<ul>
<li>Hell is a place of eternal torment. A place of darkness. A place suitable enough for the bounds of evil. A place filled with those who have murdered, killed, raped, stolen, cheated, lied and had evil thoughts. Jesus says in the book of Mark,</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>And he said, That which cometh out of the man, that defileth the man. For from within, out of the heart of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murders, Thefts, covetousness, wickedness, deceit, lasciviousness, an evil eye, blasphemy, pride, foolishness: All these evil things come from within, and defile the man.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Rev 21:8  But the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, and whoremongers, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars, shall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone: which is the second death.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Note scripture says, &quot;all liars&quot;, not some. All liars shall have their part in the lake of fire. If you have lied before, you stand condemned before a Holy God!</li>
<li>How clean are your thoughts?</li>
<li>As sure as the Sun will rise tomorrow, we have all fallen short of God's glory. Do you see it brother, do you see it sister?</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="iv.hell-is-scary">iv. Hell is scary</h5>
<ul>
<li>You think the challenges in this life are hard, there are nothing in comparison to come for the torment, pain, affliction and burning that awaits you in hell. In fact, hell will be cast into the lake of fire. There will be no respite. There will be no momentary relief. There will be no joy, there will be no laughter, only pain, only death, only destruction and continual evil.</li>
<li>Not for one lifetime, not for two, but for all eternity. All you will know is PAIN. All you will know is suffering. You have broken God's law and God in His Holiness has defined the judgement. If God was so creative to create a world as beautiful as this earth, imagine when He applies His mind to creating an eternal prison for those who have murdered, raped, blasphemed, lied and rejected Him.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="death-and-hell-ride-together">1.2 Death and Hell ride together</h4>
<h5 id="i.what-hell-is">i. What hell is?</h5>
<blockquote>
<p>Rev 6:8  And I looked, and behold a pale horse: and his name that sat on him was Death, and Hell followed with him.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Hell accompanies Death. They ride together.</li>
<li>If you have to die today, if you had to step out of this church and meet you death, where would you go?</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="ii.have-you-broken-the-law">ii. Have you broken the law?</h5>
<ul>
<li>If you have broken but just one of God's laws, you have failed to meet God's requirement for heaven.</li>
<li>Being in church, attending church does not redeem a sin committed.</li>
<li>Popes, men, money, good deeds cannot undo breaking God's law.</li>
<li>Your father, your mother, your family cannot redeem you from the judgement to come.</li>
<li>No ordinary man, no woman can stand as substitute.</li>
<li>Where are you going when you die? Have you met God's standard?</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="jesus-matters-do-you-believe-in-the-right-jesus">2. Jesus matters, do you believe in the right Jesus?</h3>
<h4 id="jesus-is-god-john-129">2.1 Jesus is God (John 1:29)</h4>
<h5 id="i.the-many-jesus">i. The many Jesus</h5>
<ul>
<li>Turn your Bibles to John, and read verse 29.</li>
<li>We see John gaze out and say a most prophetic thing.</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="ii.exposit-verse">ii. Exposit verse</h5>
<ol>
<li>Behold, gaze with intent, pay attention</li>
<li>Jesus &quot;taketh away the sin of the world&quot; (how amazing, the disciples and those closest to Him could have learnt much from these simple words of John). Yet for them they were awaiting the literal kingdom, and missed God's plan. Jesus was going to take away sin.</li>
<li>But John the Baptist, is not called the greatest prophet without reason by Jesus (Matthew 11:11). Not only is it revealed what God would do with sin, but also &quot;how&quot; He would do it.</li>
</ol>
<h5 id="iii.jesus-the-sacrifice">iii. Jesus the Sacrifice</h5>
<ul>
<li>&quot;Lamb of God&quot; - Jesus would be that way, He would be the means by which sin would be atoned. He was pointing to the cross. He was talking to Jesus being God's son. The creator dying for His creation. The son dying for the atonement of sin.</li>
<li>Does this not reflect the Holiness of God, by the payment required.</li>
<li>Does this not reflect the extreme cost for sin, God needed a payment for your sin and mine, and He His son, to be beaten, to be pierced, to walk this earth and be mocked, and to be crucified, so you and I can have freedom from sin, atonement from sin, and life eternal.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="the-real-jesus-john-11-3-14-1-john-57">2.2 The real Jesus (John 1:1-3, 14; 1 John 5:7)</h4>
<h5 id="i.the-jehovah-witness">i. The Jehovah Witness</h5>
<ul>
<li>I've run into the JW's many times, had some great conversations through the years.</li>
<li>And while I was growing up, being in an Indian school, had many muslims try to convert me.</li>
<li>But what was interesting and common hooks both used in their conversion process as a form of gateway to their religions was Jesus. Both see Jesus as a great prophet and that's it.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Mar 13:22  For false Christs and false prophets shall rise, and shall shew signs and wonders, to seduce, if it were possible, even the elect.</p>
</blockquote>
<h5 id="ii.not-the-same-jesus">ii. Not the same Jesus</h5>
<ul>
<li>Their Jesus is not our Jesus. Their Christ is not our Christ of the Bible. Their Jesus is a prophet, our's is God</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="iii.why-does-this-matter">iii. Why does this matter?</h5>
<ul>
<li>How can sins of the world be atoned for by the death of a man, even if he were perfect. Perhaps he would pay for 1 or 2. But to be the atonement for all sin, for all men and women since the dawn of time. This is significant. The payment has to be great, and the only thing that makes sense is that Christ himself, God himself becomes that payment, that atonement. Jesus MUST BE GOD FOR THE PAYMENT TO BE SUFFICIENT.</li>
<li>Only an ETERNAL PAYMENT, can stand for an ETERNAL JUDGEMENT.</li>
<li>Only an ETERNAL PAYMENT, can stand for ETERNAL SECURITY.</li>
<li>Only an ETERNAL PAYMENT, can redeem you from HELL.</li>
<li>That PAYMENT has to be Jesus Christ as GOD.</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="iv.the-supporting-verses">iv. The supporting verses</h5>
<ul>
<li><p>The verses that are irrefutable to the fact that Jesus is God is in John 1:1-3, 14-15, 1 John 5:7.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Please turn to John 1:1</p>
<ol>
<li>So we see there is the Word. This word was in the beginning with God (the Word is eternal)</li>
<li>The Word was also creator.</li>
<li>In v14, 15 we learn His identity.</li>
<li>Another irrefutable verse is 1 John 5:6-7 as it affirms Jesus is a part of the Trinity.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><p>Jesus part of the Trinity, and He is God, and He is your Savior, and He is the ONLY atonement for sin.</p>
</li>
<li><p>This is the TRUE JESUS. There is NONE OTHER.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="the-romans-road">3. The Romans Road</h3>
<h4 id="romans-323">3.1 Romans 3:23</h4>
<h5 id="i-we-are-all-guilty">i We are all guilty</h5>
<ul>
<li><p>The Bible says that all have sinned. That mean's you and I. We are sinners.</p>
</li>
<li><p>And have fallen short of God's glory.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Romans 3:10, As it is written, there is none righteous, no not one.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li><p>Do you see it friend? Your good works can't help. You could save 50 million lives but it would be insufficient to atone for the sin you have already committed in your thoughts, with your body or in your actions.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="romans-623-a">3.2 Romans 6:23 (a)</h4>
<h5 id="i.our-sin-brings-death">i. Our sin brings death</h5>
<ul>
<li>What does sin bring?</li>
<li>Well two things,
<ol>
<li>it destroys your life. Sin separates from you God, but it also pushes you further into darkness. But it can also accelerate God's judgement. If you reject His word, the Gospel and continue to pursue your own, the Lord may choose to end it.</li>
<li>secondly, sin brings the second death.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Rev 20:14  And death and hell were cast into the lake of fire. This is the second death.
And whosoever was not found written in the book of life was cast into the lake of fire.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This morning, do you see your destination?</p>
<h4 id="romans-58">3.3 Romans 5:8</h4>
<h5 id="i.god-made-a-way">i. God made a way</h5>
<ul>
<li>Death hangs of you sinner, death hangs over you. Eternal torment and condemnation.</li>
<li>But friend, but for Jesus.</li>
<li>Read Romans 5:8.</li>
<li>How amazing is our Lord, while we were yet sinners, while we were still sinful.</li>
<li>It's not about being clean and then coming, but about being contrite, being convicted of your sin, and seeing the need for you Saviour.</li>
<li>Jesus has made a way.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="romans-109">3.4 Romans 10:9</h4>
<h5 id="i.you-can-be-saved">i. You can be saved</h5>
<ul>
<li>But how can I be saved you ask? How can I be rescued from the fire?</li>
<li>Read Romans 10:9.</li>
<li>But it is not enough to confess, to speak or to think in one's mind.</li>
<li>The devil understands the scriptures. We see how he referenced it when He tried to tempt Jesus. He believes in a God, He knows God exists.</li>
<li>But that is insufficient. You have to confess and believe in thine heart. It has to be down to your core, to your innermost parts.</li>
<li>And when you have thou shalt be saved.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="romans-810">3.5 Romans 8:10</h4>
<h5 id="i.free-from-condemnation">i. Free from condemnation</h5>
<ul>
<li>The Bible says in Roman 8:1, there is no condemnation to those who are in Christ Jesus.</li>
<li>When you are saved, you are free from God's wrath, you are free from His eternal judgement.</li>
<li>Oh praise the Lord, for His work, for His redemption for you and I.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>READ Spurgeons PLEA</p>
<p>Take a moment now, and you speak to the Lord. If your heart has been convicted by the light of the gospel, call upon the Lord.
After a short moment, I will pray.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>