<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.danebalia.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.danebalia.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-25T00:31:31+02:00</updated><id>https://www.danebalia.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dane Balia</title><subtitle>This is my personal site, an expression of my learning, wisdom gained, experience and opinion.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Raising Kids As A Dad</title><link href="https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/christianity/truth/2021/07/24/raising-kids-my-lessons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raising Kids As A Dad" /><published>2021-07-24T22:16:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-24T22:16:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/christianity/truth/2021/07/24/raising-kids-my-lessons</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/christianity/truth/2021/07/24/raising-kids-my-lessons.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/raisingkids.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raising Kids&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a dad is no easy task. Men today are shunned for being masculine, condemned for who they were fundamentally designed to be and asked to tone down truth in pursuit of tolerance. In fact, the identity of men are being dissolved as our current culture relentlessly pursues addressing historic societal failures. While the pendulum is swinging the one way at full tilt, men are left in a vaccuum, some unsure, some surrendered and some going with the swing. This is at least my opinion. As such I’ve been attempting to sharpen my focus even more on what my reponsibilities are as a man, firstly towards myself, then to my beloved wife and &lt;strong&gt;especially&lt;/strong&gt; my kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This resulted in two main ideas. The first around my &lt;strong&gt;attitude&lt;/strong&gt; towards my kids, and the second my &lt;strong&gt;responsibility&lt;/strong&gt; to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enjoy-your-kids&quot;&gt;Enjoy your kids&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first lesson is simply - &lt;em&gt;enjoy your kids, all the time&lt;/em&gt;. This may seem rather simplistic but it implies that my kids are truly enjoyable and that I need to make a concerted effort to enjoy them. That doesn’t mean I find a slot of time in the day to enjoy their company, but rather at every interaction. Whether I’m stepping out of my home office to grab a coffee, or typing on my phone and they have something totally unimportant to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-infinity-and-beyond&quot;&gt;To infinity and beyond&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to first look at them and see young eyes of wonder in a complex and challenging world. Eyes who are looking to me for security, for guidance, assurance and above all relationship. How we relate to them, is how they will relate to the world. There’s so much they still need to learn, to share, to gain confidence in and we need to appreciate that journey and   enjoy it with them. They are lost in a world that is Dad and Mum. They are lost in a world where there are more problems than answers and each day despite the complete intimidation of what they don’t know they arise with a smile and a challenge to conquer the day! They are on a journey, an adventure and we have the oppurtunity to tag along. They are indeed most enjoyable, as their living the lives we led and headed towards the lives we living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;being-present&quot;&gt;Being present&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second aspect of enjoying yout kids, is being present. If they are pirates braving uncharted territory about to conquer the unknown filled with the enthusiasm that this is sure reality; who are we to upstage that with our cellphones in hand distracted by the latest FaceCrook Post or Bitter tweet. Who are we if their reality is distored by our own. I’m not saying be subservient to all their wants and needs but being present enough to stop and smell the roses. For whats on their minds however great or small; is worth acknowledging and more especially enjoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;responsibility-to-your-kids&quot;&gt;Responsibility to your kids&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My responsibility to my kids are vast. Having helped bring them into this world, it my responsibility to see to it that they are able to be effective contributors to our society, God and their family. Instead of trying to cling to very precise rules I opted for 3 general areas I try to focus my attention. Those areas are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mind&lt;/strong&gt; 🧠 &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;body&lt;/strong&gt; 🧘‍♂️&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spirit&lt;/strong&gt; 📖&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the fundamental makeup of every individual on the planet. So everyday I as a father try to feed these areas. As an example, in the morning at breakfast we all sit around the table and eat. It is here I read a portion of the Bible. I do this to provide (spirit)ual guidance, direction, morality and wisdom. After a short bible reading we engage in scenarios around it’s events (mental) - what they would do, how they would they react and bring it back to current events (including controvercies). It stimulates some amazing conversations and challenging questions. And then after that we spend about 30-40 minutes exercising. Some days its what I think they need and other days it’s exercise they would like to do (even if it’s just playing ball).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far it appears these changes have been fruitful in improving my relationship with my kiddos but far more there is a confidence in them. A confidence that comes from knowledge of life, from understanding God and from challenging their own bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kids deserve our very best and not our leftovers. Stand up dad’s, what you achieve in the workplace is nothing in comparison to what you can achieve in being a true and faithful &lt;strong&gt;father&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><category term="christianity" /><category term="truth" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">God Of Your Head</title><link href="https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/christianity/truth/2021/07/20/god-of-your-head.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="God Of Your Head" /><published>2021-07-20T18:55:22+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-20T18:55:22+02:00</updated><id>https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/christianity/truth/2021/07/20/god-of-your-head</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/christianity/truth/2021/07/20/god-of-your-head.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pottery.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pottery&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each of our minds, well those who deem themselves religious or specifically Christian have a perception of who God is. This perception is formed over time as a reflection of their minds, perhaps nurtured from adolescence, life experiences and likely from the teaching of others. This perception and the process is no small thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a piece of clay, who or what molds it determines it’s outcome. If that malleable clay is your perception of God, then the question that must be asked - how well is that perception formed? If our perception of God is poor, our actions will be equally. If our actions are poor, we are likely to make minimal impact and possibly do harm. And so it goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inexperienced potter is bound to make endless mistakes molding the clay, coming back to it, reforming it and re-evaluating it’s truths. An experienced potter however is sure, his/her hands work smoothly coming to a clay that is more or less already formed, with a shape and beauty that is a marvel. His/her perception of God is equally then a marvel and it reflects in how he/she engages with the world - through conversation, acts and thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wholly understand the analogy may have imperfections but there are two valuable lessons here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-1-be-careful-of-the-god-you-engineer-in-your-head&quot;&gt;Lesson 1: Be-careful of the god you engineer in your head.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we operate in life as if God IS and that we naturally understand who HE IS; in actuality that perception was formed, morphed and constructed over time by different processes and sources. That is, we are daily putting together the pieces of who God REALLY IS and we are either forming our own god or coming to an understanding of the REAL God. Don’t be mislead, our actions and behaviors are often unknown to us. They are refraction’s of neural thinking fed by a host of variables, sub-text and pretext. We are complex beings often acting out first and then spending time or years reflecting on why. And while we may have the best intent; how we are forming that perception of God could be entirely selfish, destructive and/or dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be-careful of the god you engineer in your head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-2-there-is-a-highly-reliable-source-for-formulating-an-understanding-of-god&quot;&gt;Lesson 2: There is a highly reliable source for formulating an understanding of God.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with a myriad of sources, processes and experiences that feed into our understanding of who God is, how can we mold the clay in a manner that we can trust, that we can use to steer our lives with and make daily decisions? And the simplicity of that answer is to take the sources, the processes and the experiences and put them to the test. The litmus test for all validity as to who God is, is found in the words of scripture. Jesus identifies Himself as the Word, in fact He promised to also preserve His words. This is our measure - the Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might say, but there are many bibles and many interpretations? Are there really? Yes there are many bibles, and yes there are hundreds if not thousands of opinions on what scripture means, but what have we done to approve and test their validity. Not all paths are equal, just like not all religions actually lead to God. The onus and responsibility of the reality of the god that is, is down to YOU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is a highly reliable source for formulating an understanding of God and it’s the Bible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><category term="christianity" /><category term="truth" /><summary type="html">In each of our minds, well those who deem themselves religious or specifically Christian have a perception of who God is. This perception is formed over time as a reflection of their minds, perhaps nurtured from adolescence, life experiences and likely from the teaching of others. This perception and the process is no small thing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Better sound: Fiio K3 and Beyerdynamic DT990</title><link href="https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/hobbies/2021/05/23/better-sound.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Better sound: Fiio K3 and Beyerdynamic DT990" /><published>2021-05-23T18:55:22+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-23T18:55:22+02:00</updated><id>https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/hobbies/2021/05/23/better-sound</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.danebalia.com/jekyll/update/hobbies/2021/05/23/better-sound.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fiiok3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fiio K3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a software developer music has proven an essential aid. From keeping me awake during late night stints to a gentle
ushering in the background when focus is called for. I have enjoyed streaming my music through the years and always
believed that I was at the pinnacle of my desktop musical experience with my high-quality &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/reviews/sennheiser-hd-448-review/&quot;&gt;Sennheiser HD 440&lt;/a&gt;. 
But most recently I was truly awakened to the fact that there was much more to pursue not by way of accessories but in audio quality. 
I had been streaming music at 44kHz while out there was a world of Hi-Res audio and even Master (studio quality). 
Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-at-44khz&quot;&gt;Audio at 44kHz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;44kHz or 44,100Hz is a common sampling frequency for analog audio, dating back to the late 1970’s in recording digital
audio on video cassettes. CDs in fact were made at 44.1kHz/16bit. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.101computing.net/sampling-sound/&quot;&gt;Sampling&lt;/a&gt;
or the sample rate is the number of samples in one second. A small sample rate or interval, results in a high sample rate 
which results in better quality sound file but then also increases the size of that audio file. This sampling of the sound wave is then 
converted into digestible binary data. So stated differently, 44,100Hz is basically 44,100 samples per second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part to the sampling is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.izotope.com/en/learn/digital-audio-basics-sample-rate-and-bit-depth.html&quot;&gt;audio bit depth&lt;/a&gt; at which that sampling
can take place. Given analog audio is a continuous wave, it has effectively infinite number of possible amplitude values. However to sample, 
we would need to define a finite set of values for these amplitude values. These values are our audio bit depth.
The more depth we have the less errors we are likely to have. A larger depth allows for more possible values at a set length (interval).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;16-bit: 65,536 values&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;32-bit: 4,294,967,296 values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/audio_bit_depth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Audio bit depth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stated differently, amplitude describes depth, and sample rate the length or interval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audio-at-hi-res&quot;&gt;Audio at Hi-Res&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why does this matter? Well depending on the sample rate and depth, you could be listening to music that is flat,
	 less lively, perhaps even lacking depth. Most streaming services today are providing you music at a depth of 16-bit
	 with an interval of 44.1kHZ. However there is a growing trend today towards Hi-res audio which is 24-bit/96kHz 
	 or 24-bit/192kHz. This more closely replicates the sound quality of musicians and engineers at their studios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is 16-bit/44.kHz terrible? Of course not. We all enjoy it. But if you looking at improving your existing experience
and you are a lover of music then it might be something worth endeavouring towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;requirements&quot;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in order to listen to Hi-Res a few things will be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firstly&lt;/strong&gt; you will need a streaming provider that supports Hi-Res or Master quality. &lt;strong&gt;Secondly&lt;/strong&gt;, you will need a digital
to analogue converter - this is because those largely provided by your PC or laptop are not specialized and of
poor quality (including Apple hardware). &lt;strong&gt;Thirdly&lt;/strong&gt; you will need a decent pair of head phones with sufficient
impedance to deliver the quality stream to your ears. &lt;strong&gt;Lastly&lt;/strong&gt; you will need to instruct your operating system to your new 
required sample rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-setup&quot;&gt;My Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a significant amount of time and effort trying to put together a working system of streaming provider, hardware
and software setup and so please feel free to leverage it or get better. The intent and drivers behind this setup
		was for me spend as little money as possible and enter the space to prove the quality of Hi-Res.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Streaming Service: &lt;a href=&quot;https://tidal.com/&quot;&gt;Tidal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DAC + Pre-Amp: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/FiiO-Headphone-Amplifier-Computer-Balanced/dp/B07KR3RF4H&quot;&gt;Fiio K3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Headphones: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0011UB9CQ/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o00_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;BeyerDynamic DT990 Pro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snags&quot;&gt;Snags&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-usb-connector&quot;&gt;No USB connector&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MacBook Pro I was using only supported 4 USB Type C. The Fiio K3 comes with USB 2.0 support and supporting cable. 
There was a possibility for me to connect it to my USB powered hub but that would have compromised
on the audio quality, and so I purchased a USB 2.0 cable (USBC male to USBC male 1.5 metre) for a direct connection
to the laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be warned that all cables are not equal, and you are specifically looking for a Type-C cable that supports USB 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-configure-sample-rate-and-interval-on-macbook&quot;&gt;How to configure sample rate and interval on MacBook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty to the Fiio K3 is that there is a light on the volume dial that let’s you know when you 
are sampling at Hi-Res or Master quality. And by default this does not happen at the OS level unless you instruct it.
The trick is go into OS-X’s Audio Midi Setup and to forcibly set the Fiio &lt;em&gt;format&lt;/em&gt; as per below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/MidiSetup.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lastly&quot;&gt;Lastly…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is this worth it? Can you actually tell the difference? Yes and yes.
I listen to classical musical and I am able to stop and take in the large forray of
instruments as they are played. The sound is warm, crisp, compartmentalized to each
instrument and just simply another level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then as a developer when I am working away furiously and in focus mode, my ability
to distinguish between 44kHz and 384kHz is little to none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you not yet convinced, and rightly so, but the setup I’ve provided might just
be cost-effective enough for you to give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><category term="hobbies" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>